<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse laying open the Beast, and his marks. Vpon the 14. of the Reuelations, vers. 9.10.11. By Richard Sheldon, a conuert from out of Babylon. Doctor in Diuinitie, His Maiesties chaplaine.</title>
            <author>Sheldon, Richard, d. 1642?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12095</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22398</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117172</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852387</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852387</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17704</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12095)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17704)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1081:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse laying open the Beast, and his marks. Vpon the 14. of the Reuelations, vers. 9.10.11. By Richard Sheldon, a conuert from out of Babylon. Doctor in Diuinitie, His Maiesties chaplaine.</title>
                  <author>Sheldon, Richard, d. 1642?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Iones, dwelling in Red-Crosse Street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation XIV, 9-11 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17704:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17704:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT PAVLES CROSSE: LAYING OPEN THE BEAST, and his MARKS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vpon the 14. of the Reuelations, verſ.</hi> 9. 10. 11.</p>
            <p>By RICHARD SHELDON, a Conuert from out of BABYLON.</p>
            <p>Doctor in Diuinitie, His Maieſties Chaplaine.</p>
            <bibl>IEREM. 50. 14.</bibl>
            <q>Put your ſelues in array againſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> round about it: all yee that bend the Bow, ſhoot at her, ſpare no Arrowes: for ſhee hath ſinned againſt the Lord.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>William Iones,</hi> dwelling in <hi>Red-Croſſe</hi> Street. 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17704:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17704:2"/>
            <head>TO THE TRVLY RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEREND, AND RELIGIOVS Doctors and Paſtors of the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Great <hi>Britaine;</hi> and namely, to <hi>Iohn</hi> D. <hi>Boys,</hi> Deane of <hi>Canterbury; Iohn</hi> D. <hi>Young,</hi> Deane of <hi>Wincheſter; Francis</hi> D. <hi>White,</hi> Deane of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lile;</hi> and to <hi>William</hi> D. <hi>Kingſley,</hi> Archd. and M. <hi>Iohn Sanford</hi> Prebend of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>R. REVEREND:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOu cannot but haue obſerued, how when in time of ignorance, errour, and tranſgreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a Riddle was propoſed in the <hi>Court</hi> of King <hi>Darius,</hi> what of all things was grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and ſtrongeſt: there were who ſtood for <hi>Wine,</hi> ſome for <hi>Kings,</hi> a third ſort for <hi>Women;</hi> but <hi>Zorobabel</hi> inlightened by the <hi>God</hi> of Truth, gaue his verdict for <hi>Truth: That Truth was of all things grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and ſtrongeſt:</hi> Which his opinion, if it were then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded by the people, approued by the <hi>Senators</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> honored and rewarded by <hi>King Darius</hi> himſelfe; we, who beleeue the manifeſtation of the <hi>Word-Truth,</hi> and the il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightning of the World by the Word of <hi>Truth;</hi> may not maruell to obſerue that <hi>Truth,</hi> now in this <hi>laſt houre (iuſtified of her own children)</hi> ſits <hi>Ouant</hi> and <hi>Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant,</hi> not onely ouer Wine, Women, and Kings, as they
<pb facs="tcp:17704:3"/>
are in the common vſance of mankind; but alſo ouer and againſt <hi>Wine, Women,</hi> and <hi>Kings,</hi> as they are abuſed by that vſurping <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Kings, Who ſits in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, out-ſhewing himſelf as if he were a God;</hi> who though by ſly contempt of <hi>Coniugall Chaſtitie</hi> (in his ſeduced <hi>Votaries</hi>) ſeemes to pretend <hi>Virginall</hi> purity, yet how vaine ſuch his pretences haue beene, the pennes of his owne haue euidently diſcouered; though hee and his would be thought not to ouer-delight in any deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacies or delicious Wines; yet in this reſpect preciſely ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; they <hi>doe carke and care for the fleſh,</hi> poſting from all quarters and coaſts, delicacies and delicious <hi>viands,</hi> and Wines for their Holy Father, and his <hi>Purpurats:</hi> yea, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding for Engliſh <hi>Seminariſts</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> not plaine <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſco,</hi> the common and vſuall briskiſh Wine of <hi>Italy,</hi> but <hi>Vino deripa</hi> Wine of the Bank (fit to beget <hi>Spaniſh Iinnets)</hi> muſt bee their <hi>cotidian</hi> liquor. Though inwords he pretend himſelfe to be <hi>Seruant of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God,</hi> yet <hi>Truth</hi> euinces him to aſſume vnto himſelfe either directly or indirectly (that is the leſt) an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertopping <hi>Soueraigntie</hi> ouer all that is <hi>ſacred</hi> and <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The preuailing of Truth againſt this Man of vntruth, hath not in any thing more euidently appeared, then in a <hi>gracious</hi> precedent <hi>illuſtration</hi> of <hi>Truth (before the powerfull and illuſtrious comming of the God of Truth)</hi> whereby he, who formerly by the <hi>Inhabitants of the Earth, was admired and adored</hi> as a <hi>Vice-God,</hi> a <hi>Vice-Chriſt;</hi> is now by the conſent of renowned <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> by the approuance of ſagest <hi>Peeres</hi> of <hi>States,</hi> by opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of iudicious <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes,</hi> by <hi>cenſure</hi> of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedeſt <hi>Clerkes</hi> in <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> found to be the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caliſtticall Beaſt</hi> himſelfe: and their <hi>Pontificious, Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotency,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17704:3"/>
and <hi>Burgheſian Eternity</hi> to be naught elſe, then the very <hi>top-crowne</hi> of <hi>Antichriſtianiſme.</hi> For the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing open and profeſsing of this kind of Truth, the Spirit of God, who in the thickeſt of <hi>Egyptian</hi> darkneſſe, did here and there in times paſt excite ſome <hi>Worthies:</hi> hath in this laſt houre, <hi>(the third, fourth, and fifth Angells, euen yet powring forth their Vialls:)</hi> Like as in other Churches others, ſo in this renowned one of Great <hi>Brittain</hi> raiſed vp you, an Armie of <hi>Valiants,</hi> arightly ordered; who with tongue and penne do happily and dexteriouſly (without ceaſing) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the ſame.</p>
            <p>To which ſeruice it hath pleaſed him, who brought me from out the <hi>Babilonian Vr,</hi> to call me, an vnworthy one, and one farre leſſe, then ſo great and <hi>gracious</hi> a <hi>miſerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> wherein, how farre and <hi>graciouſly,</hi> the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi> hath enabled me in this and my other writings, I doe with all lowly reuerent and indifferent reſpect referre and remit to you all; all Louers of <hi>Truth;</hi> and to the thrice Reuerend and venerable <hi>Sees</hi> and <hi>Chayres</hi> of your learning, the renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Vniuerſities</hi> of this <hi>Ile</hi> I ſaid with indifferent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect: for although I may not account <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them Twins in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reſpect alike, yet in regard of that <hi>Light</hi> (for the diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning betwixt <hi>Truth</hi> and falſhood) which they haue happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiued from the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Light,</hi> I dare write them, <hi>Semblable</hi> and <hi>Symbolizing O<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bs,</hi> illuſtrating this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Britaine,</hi> yea emaning forth their illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrius <hi>Beames,</hi> to the vtmoſt of the world. And by how plentifull and liber all a hand, he hath imbreathed of his <hi>Spirit</hi> into; and hath powred of his <hi>dew of Hermon</hi> vpon the <hi>Head</hi> of the moſt <hi>Gracious Primat</hi> of <hi>England</hi> (A thrice-worthy and beſt deſeruing <hi>Patron</hi> of all <hi>Conuerts,</hi> and vnder <hi>God</hi> the only Feeder of Me and Mine) vnto the very <hi>skirts of the Garment,</hi> it doth moſt linely appeare, by
<pb facs="tcp:17704:4"/>
many, not wandring, but fixed <hi>Starres,</hi> ſeated and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſplendant in this moſt illuſtrious <hi>Church</hi> of Great <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Amongſt whom, with ſpeciall and <hi>deſerued reſpect,</hi> I haue preſumed (before this my <hi>Epiſtle</hi>) to prefix the names of ſome, by them ſpeaking to you all: From them, &amp; from you all, humbly deſiring a fauourable and <hi>gracious</hi> countenancing both of Me, and Mine; in particalar of this my <hi>Argument</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Ingenuity;</hi> for following my Text cloſely, I haue endeuoured (ſuch is your wont) to open the <hi>genuine</hi> ſenſe of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> therein contained: in the proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof, if ſome bitter and tart ſpeeches againſt the Beaſt, &amp;c. do occur; from the <hi>Lord</hi> they are.</p>
            <p>Secondly of <hi>duty,</hi> for according to my bounden <hi>duty</hi> and ſeruice, I haue herein endeauoured to <hi>blazon</hi> the deſerued ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of my <hi>Soueraigne Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter:</hi> for his <hi>vndoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able integrity</hi> in the thrice holy <hi>Religion</hi> he profeſſeth, which by ſome (not peircing into the <hi>ſecrets</hi> of <hi>State</hi>) may vnworthily haue bin queſtioned.</p>
            <p>Thirdly of <hi>Sincerity,</hi> for in regard of the <hi>ſincerity</hi> of my <hi>conuerſion</hi> from out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> I dare boldly ſtile my ſelfe, <hi>A Nathaniel in whom there is no guile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, I ſaid of <hi>Zeale;</hi> for <hi>zeale</hi> againſt a certaine blaſpheming <hi>Rabſhaketh</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> hath brought forth this <hi>argument</hi> of <hi>zeale</hi> againſt the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and the obſtinate <hi>Admirers</hi> and <hi>Adorers</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt?</hi> It was my hap to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue from the hands of a worthy <hi>Knight</hi> and his <hi>Lady,</hi> a certaine blaſphemous <hi>Pamphlet</hi> (put into their hands by Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers) intitled, <hi>A humble Appeale to his moſt Excellent Maieſtie,</hi> and written by one <hi>Iohn Hunt,</hi> calling himſelfe, <hi>A Roman Catholike.</hi> This blaſphemous <hi>Rabſhaketh,</hi> I find in the ſixt Chapter of his <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> formally and vnauoyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably
<pb facs="tcp:17704:4"/>
(I ſay formally and vndeniably) blaſpheming our most <hi>Glorious God. (God bee mercifull to mee in repeating the words:)</hi> Theſe are his words, <hi>That the God of the Proteſtants</hi> (whom he knowes to be Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt) <hi>is the moſt vnciuill and euill-mannered God, of all thoſe, who haue borne the names of gods vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth: yea worſe then</hi> Pan, <hi>God of the Clownes, which can indure no Ceremonies, nor Good manners at all:</hi> Reading theſe, with diuers ſuch like, my bowels trembled within me, and my <hi>zeale</hi> for the <hi>Lord</hi> was ſet on fire, and I ſaid vnto my <hi>Soule, Spare no arrowes, but ſhoot againſt Babylon, for that ſhee hath ſinned againſt the Lord:</hi> And I ſay more againe, <hi>Anathema, Maran-atha,</hi> to him whoſe zeale for the Lord, is not with ſuch blaſphemies incenſed and ſet on fire, againſt the blaſphemers. I dare not once ſuſpect that <hi>Royall Maieſtie</hi> (though the blaſphemous Pamphlet be dedicated preſumptuouſly to it) or <hi>Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament-Excellency,</hi> or <hi>Senate-Integrity</hi> of this <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian-State</hi> hath euer had any ſpeciall notice or informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſo blaſphemous a <hi>Pamphlet;</hi> formerly in time of Conniuency, and yet ſtill (to the ioy of the <hi>Aduerſaries,</hi> and vnſpeakable ſcandall of the Pious and Godly) hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp and downe this <hi>Kingdome: Ariſe, O God,</hi> and put into the knowledge, and heart of our Soueraign, to auenge ſuch thy blaſphemous <hi>Aduerſaries,</hi> and all their witting <hi>Abettors</hi> with deſerued reproach, <hi>Amen!</hi> Wee pray againe; <hi>Ariſe, O Lord, and auenge thy owne Cauſe, and as duſt before the face of the wind, ſo ſcatter thou the Enemies of thy Glorious name, Amen,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>And ſo humbly praying, the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> to make you all perfect in the knowledge and loue of <hi>Truth;</hi> I
<pb facs="tcp:17704:5"/>
reſt a <hi>reuerent Euer-admirer</hi> of your Admirable lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in <hi>Truth:</hi> and humbly pray, that wee all may bee <hi>zealous Euer-imitators,</hi> of our <hi>Glorious</hi> and <hi>Angel</hi>-like <hi>Predeceſſours,</hi> for the <hi>Reformation</hi> and conſtant defence of that <hi>Pietie</hi> and <hi>Truth, The Teſtimony of IESVS,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, and euery one of yours, in the LORD IESVS;
Richard Sheldon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17704:5"/>
            <head>A Sermon Preached at Pauls Croſſe the firſt of <hi>September,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>APOC. 14. 9. 10. 11.</bibl>
               <q>And the third Angell followed them with a lowd voyce ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, If any man worſhip the Beaſt and his Image; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue his marke in his forhead or in his hand. The ſame ſhall drinke of the wine of Gods wrath, which is powred out without mixture into the Cuppe of his indignation. And he ſhall be tormented with fire and brimſtone in the preſence of the holy Angels, and in preſence of the Lambe. And the ſmoke of their torments aſcendeth vp for euer, and euer.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He words which I haue read in the eares of this moſt Chriſtian, and honourable Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie; are an obſcure partiall prophecie of that myſticall Booke, which (to vſe <hi>Hieromes</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Paulin:</note> phraſe) <hi>hath no more words, then it hath myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries;</hi> How then ſhall I who am of a dull ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, of a ſtammering ſpeech, and of a weake ſpirit, bee able to lay open the ſence of the ſame? except the Lyon of the Tribe of Iuda, giue me a ſpirit of courage &amp; confidence, vnleſſe the Lambe ſlaine, which hath the <hi>ſeuen eyes</hi> (that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold light of knowledge) impart vnto me ſome gratious meaſure of wiſdome and vnderſtanding. O thou <hi>Gratious Lambe,</hi> who ſcattereſt of thy graces where thou pleaſeſt; il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten my vnderſtanding, that I may truely interpret, this
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17704:6"/>
thy Scripture! O thou Powerfull <hi>Lion</hi> of <hi>Iuda; who openeſt &amp; no man ſhutteth;</hi> open thou my mouth, and ſet on fire mine af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, that I may confidently and conſtantly with a lowd voice, deliuer this thy truth, to the glory of thy great name, to the confuſion of Antichriſt, and to the eternall comfort and conſolation of our owne ſoules!</p>
            <div type="synopsis">
               <head>And the third Angell fellowed them with a lowd voyce ſaying If any man worſhip, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>MY Text (which in the whole is a moſt dreadfull Edict<note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> ſent from the Court of heauen) may be diuided into three Generall parts 1. an Inſcription or Title, <hi>And the third Angell followed them ſaying with a lowd voyce.</hi> 2. Into an Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis or Suppoſition. <hi>If any man worſhip the Beaſt and the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the Beaſt, and receaue his marke in his forhead, and in his hand.</hi> The 3. a moſt fearefull Threat, and Denounciation; <hi>the ſame ſhall drinke of the Wine of Gods wrath, which is powred forth without mixture, into the Cup of his indignation, and hee ſhall be tormented with fire and brimſtone, in preſence of the holy Angells, and of the Lambe: And the ſmoke of their torments aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vp for euer, and euer.</hi> Thus our diuiſion. And though for the auoiding of confuſion, and for breuity ſake, I doe onely thus in generall diſtinguiſh my Text, into an Inſcription, a Suppoſition, and a Denounciation; yet, if you ſhall be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to lend vnto me religious, and attentiue eares, you ſhall well obſerue, that in the proſecution thereof, I ſhall lay open vnto you, great ſecrets, of higheſt conſequence and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; prepare not your eares for any oratorious floriſhes; for ſuch, from this and like places, I for my part rather deſpiſe, then honor or admire. Wee begin with the Inſcription.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>And the third Angell followed them, ſaying with a lowd voyce, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>FOr Declaration hereof, I prefixe certaine ſuppoſitions;<note place="margin">1. Suppoſition.</note> Firſt I ſuppoſe, that which is moſt manifeſt according to the expoſition of all, to wit, that this inſcription doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17704:6"/>
vnto our conſiderations, an imaginary foreviſion of our Prophet, foreſeeing certaine zelous Preachers (typed vnto vs<note place="margin">Zealous Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers typed by the 3. Angell.</note> by this third Angell) who were with lowd, conſtant, and perſpicuous voyces, to denounce Gods fearefull iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, againſt the adorers and worſhippers of the Beaſt.</p>
               <p>Secondly wee ſuppoſe, a like manifeſt truth, (concerning<note place="margin">2. Suppoſition.</note> the circumſtance of time,) that theſe zelous Preachers (typed vnto vs by the third Angell) were immediately to follow o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Preachers &amp; Paſtours, repreſented vnto vs by other two<note place="margin">Zealous Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ioyning hand in hand for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</note> Angells, deſcribed in the 6. and 7. precedent verſes of this Chapter. The ſumme is, a certaine ranke of holy Preachers, fore-typed vnto vs by theſe three Angels immediately fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing each other through the middeſt of Heauen, (that is, publikely and manifeſtly,) were to ioyne hand in hand, in the conſormity of the Doctrines ſounded out (by the three Angells) for the reformation of the world, for the repaire of decaied Chriſtianity, and for the beating downe of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Antichriſtian ſuperſtition and idolatry. For the clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer opening of which truth of the laſt branch of this our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſuppoſition, I ſuppoſe,</p>
               <p>In the third place, that the Preachers which the Holy-Ghoſt<note place="margin">3. Su<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſition.</note> doth repreſent vnto vs by theſe three Angells, were not to appeare neere the daies of the Apoſtles, in the time of the Primatiue Church, nor for a long time after; no, they<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theſe zealous Preachers when they are to preach.</hi> 2. Theſſ. 2.</note> were not to appeare, vntill (the Diuells being let looſe) the Antichriſtian ſtate was to be reuealed, and the <hi>miſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity by the breath of Chriſts mouth,</hi> was by degrees to be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; a truth ſo manifeſt, that there is no colour to gainſay it; for againſt the Beaſt, the adorers thereof, and the receiuers of the Beaſts markes, theſe Preachers (typed by Angells) were to ſound forth their doctrines of reformation; I ſay doctrines<note place="margin">Preachers of Reformation</note> of reformation, for by inuincible arguments it may bee made manifeſt (which for breuity, I muſt omit) that theſe Preachers are to bee reputed of the number of thoſe, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is ſaid, that they <hi>were to propheſy againe, before many peoples, &amp;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apoc. 10. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Nations, and tongues, and Kings. Propheſy againe</hi> ſaith the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17704:7"/>
of God; why againe? but for the reformation of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious perfection of Chriſtianity, decayed and ruinated, by the tirany of the Beaſt.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, I ſuppoſe, that vpon the Preaching of ſuch Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors,<note place="margin">4. Suppoſition.</note> typed vnto vs by Angels; effects anſwerable to their doctrines, were infallibly to enſue; a generall reformation of<note place="margin">Reformation in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallsbly to follow vpon the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of theſe Preachers. <hi>Math. 24.</hi>
                  </note> the world; the fall of Babilon, the Throane and Seate of the Beaſt; &amp; alſo great zeale of Chriſtians, for their vtter deteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the markes of the Beaſt; <hi>for heauen and earth ſhall paſſe and be changed, but the word of God ſhall not paſſe away vnaccom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From out of theſe ſuppoſitions not to be gainſaid; I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce<note place="margin">A concluſion moſt euident for the honor of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed churches.</note> this concluſion; that where and when, wee firſt find a rank of godly Preachers ſounding out in their due order the doctrines of theſe three Angells, with anſwerable effects fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing thereupon; that there, then, and by them, wee muſt take this Propheſy of the Holy-Ghoſt, to bee accompliſhed and fulfilled. And ſo wee come to obſerue, what the Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines of theſe three Angells are, what their order of deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of them is, and withall to make moſt cleare application of the Propheſy, to the Doctours and Paſtours of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The firſt Angell,</hi> deſcribed verſe 6. <hi>flyes through the middeſt of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">v. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>heauen, hauing an euerlaſting Goſpell, that hee might preach the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Doctrine of the firſt Angell, the groundworke from whence all Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches haue begun their reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
                  <hi>ſame to the inhabitants of the earth, to euery nation, tongue, tribe, and people; ſaying with a lowd voyce, feare God, and giue him glory, for the houre of his iudgement is come, and worſhip him, who made heauen and earth, the ſea and fountaines of waters.</hi> And is not this the firſt principle for reformation, (feare God and giue him glory,) the euerlaſting Goſpell, whereon, the Doctours and Paſtours of the reformed Churches, haue begun their doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine of reformation, and haue laid open the Idolatrous en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ormities, and ſuperſtitious myſteries of the Antichriſtians? This they haue proteſted to Counſells, ſo they haue profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to Kings and States, <hi>their ſound hath gone forth into the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>whole earth, and their words haue</hi> (and ſhall) <hi>ſpread abroad into
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17704:7"/>
the ends of the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſecond Angell</hi> in the 8. verſe ſounds out, the ruine &amp;<note place="margin">v. 8.</note> fall of Babilon; <hi>She is fallen, ſhe is fallen, Babilon that great City is fallen, for ſhee hath made all Nations drinke of the Wine of her whoredoms.</hi> And haue we not here the neuer intermitted cries, voyces, <hi>alleluiahs,</hi> and exultations of the Doctours and Paſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours<note place="margin">The Doctrine of the ſecond Angel deliuered and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed churches.</note> of the Reformed Churches reioycing againſt <hi>Babilon,</hi> the ſeat of <hi>Antichriſt?</hi> in regard of the great errours and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections thereof (vpon their doctrines and preachings) partly reioycing for ſo much as is already accompliſhed, in <hi>Germany, Bohemia, Swethland, Denmarke, England, France, Burgundy,</hi> and elſewhere, partly fore-preaching her vtter ruine and deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to bee at hand, euen then, when the fifth <hi>viole of Gods</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apoc. 16. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>wrath ſhall be caſt into the Throane of the Beaſt,</hi> the very Seate of the Antichriſtian ſtate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The third Angell</hi> followes, denouncing (according as my<note place="margin">in the 9. 10. 11. verſe. <hi>The Doctrine of the third Angell with anſwerable effects in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed churches.</hi>
                  </note> text hath it) Gods eternall wrath againſt all thoſe, <hi>who ſhould worſhip the Beast, and the image of the Beaſt, and ſhould receaue his character in their hands, orforeheads.</hi> And are not ſuch the neuer intermitted forewarnings, and doctrines of the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches, earneſtly (and in Gods name) perſwading euery perſon, to renounce all manner of communion with the Antichriſtian Synagogue of <hi>Rome,</hi> the effects of which their doctrines and perſwaſions, how glorious they haue bin, what eye obſerues not, and what Chriſtian heart ioyes not to haue obſerued?</p>
               <p>Theſe things being thus manifeſt, ſhall we not henceout<note place="margin">Applicatió of the propheſy moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident in the Pastours of the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</note> inferre moſt clearely, that the Paſtours of the Reformed Churches, are the very men who were fore-typed by theſe three Angells, ſounding out <hi>the feare and worſhip of God alone,</hi> denouncing forth <hi>the ruine of Babilon?</hi> threatning aloud, moſt heauie iudgements againſt all thoſe, <hi>who ſhould worſhip the Beaſt, and the image of the Beaſt, and receaue the marke of the Beaſt in their hands or on their foreheads?</hi> we ſay, and truly ſay;<note place="margin">Iſa. 41. 23.</note> (for it is an argument of Gods owne making) If any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſhall foretell things before they do happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if the things
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17704:8"/>
foretold, doe happen according as they are foretold that they ſhould happen; that the foretellers of ſuch things, are to bee reputed for true Prophets. Why then ſhall we not anſwere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably ſay, that theſe things, which happen agreeingly to a fore-propheſy, of Gods owne Spirit, &amp; accordingly as Gods Spirit hath foretold that they ſhould happen? that they are the very things, which the Spirit of God did fore tell ſhould ſo happen? If then the Paſtours and Doctours of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches, doe the very things, Preach the very Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines, obſerue the very order in their doings and preachings, which the Spirit of God vnder the type of theſe three An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells, hath foretold, ſhould be ſo done, ſhould be ſo preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhould be ſo obſerued, againſt the Beaſt and Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſtate of <hi>Rome,</hi> for the reformation of decayed Chriſtianity; why then, are not they the very men, whom the holy-Ghoſt hath here by theſe three Angells fore-ſhewed vnto vs. The full accompliſhing of any Propheſy is the opening, yea is the<note place="margin">Ire<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> lib. 4. 42.</note> proofe of a Propheſy; a kind of proofe, often vſed by the Scriptures, when they adde and atteſt. <hi>That it might be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 1. 22. &amp; 2. 15. Iohn 15. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>which was ſpoken by the Prophets, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Propheſy is accompliſhed in the Reformed Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, moſt punctually; aſſuredly then, the truth and intent of the Propheſy, aymed at them, and intended them: diſſolue me this riddle yee Pontificialls, either you for your ſelues, or (in your behalfe) ſome of your fauourites, I meane newtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizing Interim-iſts; pretended Pacificatours, but in truth <hi>Romes</hi> ſubdolous factours!</p>
               <p>It cannot bee denied (our Aduerſaries will ſay) but that the Preachers of the Reformed Churches, haue pretended to<note place="margin">An <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uaſion of the Aduerſary moſt idle.</note> beginne all their reformation from the Doctrine of the firſt Angell, <hi>feare God, giue him glory, and worſhip him alone;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it be denied, but that they are frequent in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uectiues againſt <hi>Rome</hi> Popiſh, as againſt <hi>Babilon;</hi> and withall that they doe deteſt, and diſwade all manner of communion, with the Pope and with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> neither can it be denied that vpon ſuch their preachings, effects anſw<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17704:8"/>
to their pretences haue followed, falls and defections of diuerſe States &amp; Kingdomes from the <hi>Pope;</hi> yet for that they miſtake their marke, in inueighing againſt our Holy Father the <hi>Pope</hi> (Chriſts Vicar) inſteed of <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> barking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> (which is the moſt chaſt Spouſe of Chriſt,) as againſt the Beaſts throane and ſeate; here hence it is, that we deſeruedly account them as fore-runners of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, but not any rank or order of Godly Preachers, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignified by theſe three Angells: ſo <hi>Briſtow,</hi> ſo <hi>Harding,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwere.</note> ſo <hi>Saunders,</hi> ſo <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> ſo the whole army of Papall <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies.</hi> O the vanity of this ſubterfuge! who ſhall teach vs what is the beaſt, and where is the throane and ſeate of the beaſt, if not thoſe very men who by the Spirit of God haue beene fore-ſigned for that function, and in whom euery iot of the Propheſy is accompliſhed? O the idleneſſe of this eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion! doth the ſpirit of God fore-expreſſe no other proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and tokens of thoſe Preachers, (which were to inueigh againſt Antichriſt and his ſeate,) then ſuch as the very fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners of Antichriſt ſhould to the full performe &amp; practiſe? O the impiety of this pretence, to affirme, that the fore-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Antichriſt, ſhall builde their preachings vpon theſe foundations, <hi>Feare God, giue him glory and worſhip him alone;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 4. 11.</note> and vpon this, <hi>there is no name giuen vs vnder heauen for ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but the name of Ieſus, and of the Lambe.</hi> If we had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">The calumnious and irreligious reaſoning of our Aduerſaries.</note> proofes, to conuince the Pope to be an Antichriſt, yet this would abundantly ſuffice, for that they account the Doctours and Paſtours of the Reformed Churches to bee fore-runners of Antichriſt; in regard they contend, to bound all true religious worſhip, within that principle: <hi>Feare God, giue him glory, and worſhip him alone;</hi> and for that they ſumme<note place="margin">Acts 4. 12.</note> vp all happines of Faith within that Apoſtolicall decree, <hi>there is no name giuen vs vnder heauen by which we muſt be ſaued but the name of Ieſus;</hi> Ieſus that Lambe, which ſolely and alone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>taketh away the ſinnes of the world.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thus haue wee by a breefe examination of the inſcription (our firſt generall part) made a doore of entrance, for the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17704:9"/>
ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoſe great myſteries and difficulties, which lie hid and couered in our ſecond part, the <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> and ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which (the Spirit of God inabling,) wee ſhall now indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to lay open, and declare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>If any one worſhip the Beaſt, and his Image, and receiue<note place="margin">Second Generall part, the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis or Suppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> his marke in his hand or forehead, the ſame, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>HErein conſiſts the greateſt (I may ſay all) difficulty of our Text, not in reſpect of the perſons, againſt whom the Suppoſition is made; for the <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> being vniuerſall and indefinit, (<hi>If any</hi>) it includes all, excludes none; All, Emperours, Kings, Princes, States, Nobles, Gentles, Peoples, Young or Old, Rich or Poore; all; <hi>If any one worſhip the Beaſt, and the Image of the Beaſt; or receiue his marke in hand, or on fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, they ſhall ſurely drinke of the wine of Gods wrath:</hi> neither is their any difficulty to declare the ſenſe of the word wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>If any one ſhall worſhip or adore the Beaſt, or the image of the Beaſt;</hi> for who is ſo ignorant as not to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue,<note place="margin">The worſhip here condemned is a diuine religious worſhip, not a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill reuerence.</note> that the adoration and worſhip here ſpoken of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, is not a ciuill worſhip or politicke adoration giuen to any ciuill Authority or Maieſty? no, no; it is a religious and diuine (both externe and interne) worſhip, giuen to the <hi>State</hi> and <hi>See</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt;</hi> and this, vpon the acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a diuine and Godlike kinde of Dignity and Maieſty reſiding in the Beaſt, or in the Supreame head of that State, which is typed by the Beaſt; as hereafter wee ſhall more fully<note place="margin">Wherein conſiſts the difficulty of this text.</note> declare; wherein then conſiſts all the difficulty? ſurely in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring what is meant by the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> what by the <hi>image of the Beaſt,</hi> what by the <hi>taking of the Beaſts marke either in hand or</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bellar: de Rom. pont: lib. 3. Cap. 11. 15. Viega<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> et Ribera in Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip: Chriſtophorſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> treat: of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt againſt Downam part: 2. Chapt. 8. alij.</note> 
                  <hi>on forehead.</hi> O thou <hi>Lyon</hi> of <hi>Iuda, thou that openeſt, and no hand ſhutteth,</hi> reueale this miſtery vnto vs.</p>
               <p>Here we firſt obſerue by the way (and I deſire your atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) the <hi>feuer-trepidation,</hi> and ignorance of certaine prime Ignatian &amp; other Pontifician <hi>Rabbies;</hi> who, fearing the true myſticall ſenſe of this place, doe (again ſtall antiquitie, and their owne tenents) hold themſelues to the very letter of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17704:9"/>
the prophecie; affirming, that the followers of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhall be compelled to adore and worſhip, a true reall <hi>beaſt;</hi> and a true reall <hi>Image of a Beaſt;</hi> (wee muſt interprete them of a Beaſt hauing ſo many heads and hornes with Diadems ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as is deſcribed by the Prophet) and alſo, that they ſhall be<note place="margin">Ier. 13.</note> enforced like F<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lons (by reall inuſtion) or like the Prieſts<note place="margin">A moſt imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſubterfuge of our Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries.</note> of <hi>Baal,</hi> by cruell inciſion, to receiue a reall marke of the Beaſt in <hi>their hands,</hi> or on <hi>their foreheads.</hi> Which their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfuge while I deliuer, doe yee ſmile at their follies? or frowne at their impudencies? or bewaile their obſtinacies? Perhaps you will rather admire, what may be the reaſon, why they flie to ſo doting an interpretation; which if they doe, then bee pleaſed to take the reaſon thereof to be this. Many Doctors and Paſtors of the reformed Churches (ſo alſo his<note place="margin">Praemonit. pag. 111.</note> moſt <hi>Excellent Maieſtie,</hi> in his <hi>Premonition to Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi>) doe verily obiect againſt the <hi>Pope</hi> and his, that by the adoration of the Beaſt, and the Image of the Beaſt, and by the taking of the Beaſts marke in the hand, or on the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, is moſt liuely (in a true myſticall ſenſe) typed forth<note place="margin">No man kiſsing the Popes feet, omits him ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration both going and comming; &amp; when he kiſſes he is well nigh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to the ground. The forme and Ground of all Papall faith.</note> the <hi>Papall Antichriſtian State,</hi> with the anſwerable practiſes thereof; of their adoring the <hi>Popes</hi> Perſon with Diuine and religious adoration; of their Soule-ſubiection to him, in the vorie tye and band of ſupernaturall faith, and ſacred obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to his damnable lawes, and forged traditions: ſo that, as in a true ſenſe it may bee an Article of Faith (yea the forme and ground of all their faith) in that Church, <hi>Wee beleeue our holy Father the Pope;</hi> ſo it may bee likewiſe a new princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of religious worſhip with them; <hi>Wee adore and worſhip our Holy Father the Pope:</hi> and as for their taking of diuers ſuperſtitious markes, of communion, vnder him in their hands and foreheads, what more manifeſt? as wee ſhall anon moſt fully declare.</p>
               <p>Now the <hi>Pontificians,</hi> to auoid this grieuous imputation ſticking ſo cloſe to their ſides) knowing for certaine, that not any of their Popes euer as yet, erected any ſuch reall Beaſt, or reall Image of Beaſt (as is deſcribed by Saint <hi>Iohn</hi>)
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17704:10"/>
to bee adored and worſhipped; <hi>hauing ſo many heads and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Why Popiſh Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies dreame of a reall Beaſt to be ſet vp by Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt for adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
                  <hi>hornes,</hi> in proportion <hi>like a Leopard;</hi> hauing the <hi>feete of a Beare,</hi> and <hi>the mouth of a Lion:</hi> Againe, they knowing for certaine, that their <hi>Popes</hi> as yet neuer compelled their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers to receiue any rcall markes by <hi>inuſtion,</hi> or <hi>inciſion, in their hands, or vpon their foreheads:</hi> Here hence it is, that they are ſo ſtrongly addicted, to the litterall interpretation of this prophecie, of a reall Beaſt, of a reall Image, and of the reall adoring and worſhipping of the ſame; together with the receiuing of reall markes of the Beaſt, by inciſion or by inuſtion, in their hands, or on their foreheads. But O the vanity of this ſo doting an interpretation! How verified a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt<note place="margin">Pſal. 49. 13.</note> them, is that of the Prophet? <hi>Man being in honour, hath not vnderſtood, hee hath beene compared with the beaſts, and been made like vnto them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For againſt this their vanitie, many contrarieties, impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, and abſurdities doe concurre? Contrarieties againſt<note place="margin">Their vaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, &amp; againſt their owne Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents.</note> the ioynt interpretation of all the <hi>Auntients;</hi> who all of them (none excepted) doe interprete the Beaſt, either <hi>for the whole multitude of the wicked;</hi> or for the <hi>wicked State and Empire of Antichriſt himſelfe:</hi> Contrariety againſt their owne doctrine, they all generally affirming, that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhall ſuppreſſe all manner of <hi>Idolatry;</hi> what likelihood then, that hee ſhall ſet vp ſo abſurd and miſhapen a beaſt, or image of the beaſt for idolatrous adoration and worſhip? Contrarietie againſt their owne doctrine; diuers of them teaching, that the <hi>Beaſt</hi> ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth<note place="margin">Contrarieties againſt the ſame.</note> forth and ſignifieth by one of his heads, the very State and Empire of Antichriſt himſelfe; yea <hi>Bellarmine</hi> (frequent<note place="margin">Bellar. de Rom. Pont. lib. 3. c. 5.</note> in his ouerſight and contradictions) affirmeth as much.</p>
               <p>Againe, how many impoſſibilities doe preſent themſelues againſt this their interpretation, of ſuch a reall beaſt, reall markes, reall inuſtions and inciſions? Impoſſibilitie; for how<note place="margin">Bell. lib. 3. de Rom. Pont. c. 8.</note> poſſible, that within the ſpace of three yeeres and a halfe (the full time of the Beaſts reigne, in the opinion of all <hi>Pontifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans) that the whole earth</hi> (the Inhabitants of the whole earth) <hi>ſhould be</hi> brought perſonally and preſentially <hi>to adore and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:17704:10"/>
ſuch a Beaſt? what? ſhall the faire Beaſt bee carried vp and downe, from Countrey to Countrey like their Holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, vpon mens ſhoulders; or like their <hi>Siluer-ſhrines,</hi> vpon mens backes? or like their <hi>God of bread;</hi> by their handes in <hi>Siluer-turretts?</hi> or ſhall it (<hi>Dagonlike</hi>) bee reared and ſet vp for a <hi>Pilgrimage-ſtocke</hi> in ſome Wood, or Groue, or in ſome Chappell? as at <hi>Loretto, Mount-ſerrat<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Sichem?</hi> or ſhall this adoration onely bee done, by ſome <hi>Puppet-images</hi> (in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes of the Beaſts ſworne deuouts) like thoſe of <hi>Diana,</hi> or like thoſe their boſome-Godlings, worne by diuers of their <hi>deuouts</hi> in their boſomes, prettie ſmall Images; of their Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges adored, and worſhipped at <hi>Loretto, Mountſerrato, Sichem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Impoſsibilities againſt the ſame.</note> and elſewhere? Anſwere, O yee our Aduerſaries, (and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries of Gods truth) how this adoration of ſuch a reall Beaſt, or Image of the Beaſt, ſhall be performed by the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the earth?</p>
               <p>Againe, impoſſibilities; for how ſhall ſuch a Beaſt (except it be a liuing <hi>Gereon</hi>-like monſter) fight his battailes? What weapons ſhall hee vſe for the <hi>ouercomming of Gods Saints?</hi> In what manner and forme of gouernment ſhall hee rule and gouerne the <hi>whole earth?</hi> how ſhall hee <hi>ſpeake,</hi> or what lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage ſhall it vſe? how ſhall one of the <hi>Beaſts heads be cut off,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apoc. 13.</note> ſo that the Beaſt ſhall thereupon dye, and yet bee reuiued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine? Let our Aduerſaries remoue theſe impoſſibilities (with many ſuch like) or elſe let them ceaſe to dreame any longer, after ſo doting a conceit, of a reall Beaſt, or Image of a beaſt, to bee ſet vp by Antichriſt, to bee worſhipped and adored.</p>
               <p>Beſides contraricties and impoſſibilities; how abſurd alſo<note place="margin">Abſurdities a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſame.</note> is this their <hi>Paradoxe?</hi> how abſurd to thinke, that wily <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt,</hi> ſhould reare vp ſuch a beaſt to bee adored? How ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, that the whole world ſhould bee drawne to the adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch a beaſt? How abſured to dreame, that the <hi>reall</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ribera</hi> apud <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ga<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> &amp; Vitgas</hi> in cap. 13. apoc. ſect. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>marke or image of a Dragon</hi> (ſo <hi>Ribera</hi> the <hi>Ieſuite</hi>) or that the <hi>picture of Antichriſts owne perſon</hi> (ſo <hi>Viegas</hi> the <hi>Ieſuite</hi>) ſhould by reall inuſtion, impreſſion, or inciſſion, be burnt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17704:11"/>
or cut, into the very hands and fore-heads, of the followers of <hi>Antichriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. Yee, who pretend to bee followers and admirers of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Antiquitie: yea, your <hi>Tridentine</hi> Fathers command you, not to interpret the Scriptures, againſt the vnanimous conſent of the Ancients; tell vs, who, or how many of the Antient Fathers euer dreamed of this your conceite of ſuch reall <hi>beaſts, markes, inuſtions,</hi> or <hi>inciſions?</hi> True it is ſomefew, but thoſe not very antient, as <hi>Primaſius</hi> and <hi>Ansbertus</hi> haue affirmed, that the marke of the Beaſt ſhall bee compoſed of<note place="margin">Apud Viogam in Apoc. 13.</note> three Greeke letters P T X which ioyned and framed into one forme and figure, doe compendiouſly repreſent the name of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But this their conceit, by no meanes pleaſeth our Aduerſaries, for thereout it may be inferred, that (in the opinion of the Ancients) <hi>Antichriſts myſtery of iniquity,</hi> ſhall be a pretenſed miſtery, vnder the very name of <hi>Christ;</hi> A very <hi>Vice-gerency</hi> in the ſtead and place of Chriſt; the very thing, which the Pope arrogantly aſſumes to himſelfe; that which his flatterers doe attribute vnto him; that, for which all the <hi>world admires after him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus haue wee laid open and refuted the interpretation of our Aduerſaries, wee come now to declare the true ſenſe of theſe words. I pray againe, O thou <hi>God,</hi> who art the reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler<note place="margin">Our prayer.</note> of all ſecrets, reueale this thy truth vnto vs! Firſt, of the Beaſt, and of the Image of the Beaſt in <hi>abſtracto</hi> what they are, afterwards in <hi>concreto</hi> and by way of application, where<note place="margin">Gerſon. tract. contra hereſin dei communio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſub vtra ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. to. 1. p. 522. Ambroſ. ſer. 8. in Pſal. 118. Dan. 7. <hi>What the Beaſt is, &amp; that a very State &amp; wicked Empire is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſignified.</hi>
                  </note> they are, who they are.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>If any one adore the Beaſt, and the Image of the Beaſt, &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>IF wee compare Scripture with Scripture (<hi>the beſt rule and ſureſt way for interpretation;</hi>) then agreeing to the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of all the Ancients, wee ſhall find, that as in <hi>Daniel,</hi> by the <hi>foure beaſts ariſing from out of the Sea,</hi> were ſignified the foure <hi>Monarchies</hi> of the world; the <hi>Aſſirian, Perſian, Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian,</hi> and the <hi>Roman:</hi> ſo likewiſe here, by the beaſt ariſing out of the Sea, with ſuch a varietie of <hi>hornes, heads,</hi> and <hi>dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dems;</hi>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:17704:11"/>
wee are to vnderſtand ſome Prime or Principall <hi>State,</hi> or <hi>Empire</hi> (hauing either ſucceſſiuely or ioyntly different formes of Gouernment) to be preſignified and fore-ſhewed:<note place="margin">Bell. de Antich. cap. 5. &amp; 15.</note> which is ſo apparent a truth, that the <hi>Pontifician Rabbies</hi> themſelues, yea <hi>Bellarmine</hi> (their <hi>Hercules</hi>) acknowledgeth it for very probable, that the <hi>Apocalipticall beaſt, with ſo many heads, hornes, and diadems, doth ſignifie the Roman State, with their ſeuerall formes of Gouernment;</hi> yea and that by <hi>one of the heads is ſignified,</hi> the moſt wicked and execrable <hi>State of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt himſelfe.</hi> Thus haue wee found, what is typed by the beaſt; if then we will reſolue, the <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> and ſuppoſition, it is thus: If any one worſhip the beaſt; that is, if any one worſhip and acknowledge the State of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> &amp;c. But<note place="margin">
                        <hi>What the Image of the Beaſt is.</hi>—</note> what is the Image of this Beaſt, which is likewiſe forbid, vnder moſt fearefull puniſhment, to bee worſhipped and adored?</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Image</hi> of any thing, muſt bee a ſpeciall reſemblance, of that wherof it is an Image; If perfect and naturall, it muſt<note place="margin">Two ſorts of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</note> haue a likeneſſe, not only repreſentatiue, but alſo in nature, and being of <hi>exiſtence;</hi> ſo the naturall ſonne, is a perfect image of his father, like in repreſentation, and like in being and exiſtence: If the image bee imperfect; then, though it bee different from the thing (whereof it is an image) in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and being (as the image of a man, drawne by the Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter on a Tablet) yet in forme and vertue of repreſenting, it muſt haue a repreſentatiue forme of likeneſſe, as the ſame<note place="margin">The Image of the Beaſt may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in a double ſenſe.</note> image drawen by the Painter hath: Now then, the image of that State, or forme of Gouernment, which is ſignified by the beaſt, may either bee a perfect image thereof, like in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting, and like in exiſtence and being, to weet, a State repreſenting that State; one wicked forme of Gouernment repreſenting another; or elſe it may be an imperfect image, in ſome likeneſſe either by expreſſion of the penne of the Writer, or the pencill of the Painter, repreſenting the ſame.<note place="margin">Sarisburg. in policrat. l. 5. c. 16. fol. 169.</note> For example, wee may take the formes of gouernment of Papall <hi>Legates</hi> and <hi>Nuncios,</hi> ſent forth (to vſe <hi>Sarisburienſis</hi>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:17704:12"/>
his words) <hi>from the preſence of Satan, for the diſſipation and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Church;</hi> Wee may (I ſay) take them, for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect images (becauſe of like nature) and alſo repreſenting the abſolute, ſacred Monarchy of their Holy Fathers the<note place="margin">The State-Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine an Image of the State-Papall.</note> Popes; a State <hi>Legatine,</hi> repreſenting a State <hi>Papall:</hi> but for inperfect Images, wee may either take that, which is done by the adulatorious pens of the <hi>Canoniſts,</hi> deſcribing the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute ſtate, or ſacred <hi>Numen</hi> of their Lord <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> or<note place="margin">A threefold I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the State-Papall.</note> that, which by the <hi>Popes</hi> themſelues is expreſſed, in their <hi>Bulls, Conſtitutions, Clementines, Decretalls,</hi> or <hi>Extrauagants;</hi> or finally that, which the Painter, <hi>Statuary,</hi> or Gold-Smith, performes in painting, caruing, or caſting of the <hi>Popes</hi> ſacred <hi>Tiare,</hi> or <hi>Triple-crowne:</hi> by which ſacred <hi>Tiare,</hi> or triple Crowne, is repreſented vnto vs, a liuely image of the <hi>Papall</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Papall Tiare, or triple crowne an Image of the Papall State.</note> State, both in heauen aboue, below on earth, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath euen in hell it ſelfe. In heauen by the top-crowne thereof; for it being moſt certaine, that no man can enter into heauen, except abſolued from his ſinnes; ſo likewiſe in the <hi>Papall</hi> ſtate it is as aſſured, that none can be abſolued from their ſinnes, but by authoritie deriued from the <hi>Pope,</hi> yea, and in caſes <hi>papal</hi> and reſerued, either the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelfe in perſon, or his chiefe <hi>Penitentiary</hi> muſt abſolue, and ſo vnlock heauen gates, or elſe there can bee no entrance thereinto. By his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond crowne, is ſignified, that his power vpon earth; vnto which it is neceſſary, vnder the forfeit of ſaluation (ſo defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <hi>Pope Boniface) that euery humane Creature be ſubiect;</hi> nay,<note place="margin">Bonif. vnam Sanctam de maioritate.</note> it is not enough for euery one in particular and <hi>(ipſo facto) in very deede,</hi> to bee ſubiect to ſuch his power; but euery one out of neceſſitie of ſaluation, muſt further beleeue, that all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, euen euery <hi>humane Creature, is ſubiect thereunto.</hi> O pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption! it is not enough, for a man in himſelfe to bee <hi>ipſo facto, by very deed</hi> ſubiect to the <hi>Pope,</hi> to giue vnto him his <hi>Soule</hi> and <hi>Conſcience,</hi> in faith and obedience; but hee muſt further profeſſe and beleeue (with a diuine faith) all the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of <hi>Chriſtianitie</hi> to bee ſubiect vnto him. Loe how Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereminent his Monarchie is vpon earth; <hi>exalting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe</hi>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:17704:12"/>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>ouer all that which is called God; or which is called Auguſtum, ſacred.</hi> Now his power ouer Hell (for Purgatory is in the ſuburbs of Hell) ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the third and laſt of his triple-crownes, is ſo ſacred and ſo abſolute; that hee can faſten vpon baſe creatures (<hi>Graines</hi> and <hi>Meddalls</hi>) ſuch a ſauing power, and efficacie, that whoſoeuer ſhall vſe the ſame; with ſuch conditions as by his fatherhood are preſcribed; hee ſhall thereby, deliuer ſoules (more or fewer) out of the flames of their imagined <hi>purgatory.</hi> Loe how <hi>Pape,</hi> a word of wonder, comes from <hi>Papa</hi> the worlds wonder.</p>
                  <p>Thus haue we expreſſed, what is meant by the Beaſt, and<note place="margin">What is the Beaſts marke.</note> by the image of the Beaſt; now come wee to declare, what is the Beaſts marke, what the taking thereof, whether in hand or on forehead. I ſhould trifle the time, contemne all learned Antiquitie, fall into a laberinth of <hi>contrarieties, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilities,</hi> and <hi>abſurdities,</hi> if I ſhould but onely dreame of a corporall marke to bee ingrauen by inciſion, or to be burnt by inuſtion (as the faſhion of men is to do with their cattell)<note place="margin">Praemonit. pag. 111.</note> in the hands, or vpon the foreheads of <hi>Antichriſts</hi> followers: no, no; the marke muſt bee <hi>metaphoricall</hi> (as his Maieſtie moſt excellently) by ſome rite of profeſſion; it muſt bee <hi>myſticall,</hi> by ſome rite of ſubiection; the marke on the forehead, ſome ſacrilegious ceremonie, whereby the authoritie of that Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous<note place="margin">The marks of the Beaſt not reall by inciſion or inuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; diuers rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for the ſame.</note> State is profeſſed: the marke in the handes, ſome like impious ceremonie, or thing accepted of in the hand, whereby ſubiection and obedience to that wicked State is performed. And this without all doubt, is moſt agreeing to truth: (to truth I ſay) for as the markes of <hi>Chriſt</hi> his flocke,<note place="margin">2. Timoth. 2. 9. Greg. 29. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. cap. 2.</note> are not any reall <hi>markes,</hi> by inciſion or inuſtion: but the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of his faith, with obedience to him, with the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of ſome religious <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> or godly <hi>Sacraments</hi> taken for that purpoſe: ſo likewiſe, ſhall the markes of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chriſts markes miſticall and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall; ſo the marks of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</note> and <hi>Antichriſtian State</hi> (for <hi>contraries are of the ſame kinde</hi>) bee ſome ſacrilegious ceremonies, or ſacraments. Againe, agreeing to truth; becauſe ſuch markes, being requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17704:13"/>
as neceſſary for allowed commerce in the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> State; moſt meete, that they ſhould be anſwerably taken, like to other markes of humane ſocietie and communication. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing to truth; becauſe they being taken, as markes of a continued religious (or rather ſuperſtitious) worſhip, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition<note place="margin">The markes of the Beaſt to be reiterated.</note> of ſuperſtitious acts, whereby faith and obedience to Antichriſt is acknowledged; moſt meet, that they ſhould bee ſuch, as may be often reiterated. For we may not thinke that <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> a moſt ambitious and arrogant <hi>Lord,</hi> will bee contented with an once, and a one ſubiection, ſignified by a marke once violently imprinted: no, no, this will not ſerue his turne; for howſoeuer, the hearts of his followers may ſtand affected to him, yet hee will aſſuredly require very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent acts and rites of profeſſion, and obedience to bee made vnto him: what neede then of ſuch a horſe-like impreſſion, that cannot bee reiterated? Further, moſt agreeing to truth: for it being moſt certaine (and let the Aduerſaries deny this if they can) that the adoration of the Beaſt, and of the Image of the Beaſt, and the taking of the Beaſts marke in hand, or vpon forehead, ſhall bee ſome ſuperſtitious ſeruices, and ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous worſhips yeelded to the Beaſts State, yea the primeſt of his ſeruices: Why then, ſhall not the ſame bee performed by ſome flagitious acts, or ſakerments of ſubiection vnto the Beaſts State?</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, moſt agreeing to the truth, for if <hi>the name of the</hi>
                     <note place="margin">An vnauoydable reaſon &amp; proofe.</note> 
                     <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and <hi>the number of the name of the Beaſt,</hi> bee not by reall <hi>characters,</hi> to bee written in the hands, or vpon the foreheads of <hi>Antichriſts</hi> followers (as it is moſt manifeſt, and our Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries deny not) but only <hi>myſtically</hi> to be taken, for that they ſhall bee either called after his name, or after the number of his name: for example, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ither <hi>Papiſts</hi> after the name <hi>Papa,</hi> (a name which <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeuenth decreed ſhould be peculiar to the <hi>Popes</hi> alone) or elſe <hi>Latines</hi> or <hi>Romanes,</hi> after the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber<note place="margin">Dictat. Greg. 7. apud Bar<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. ann. 1175.</note> of his name, Latines, after <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Romans after <hi>Hebr. Romijt.</hi> Why then, ſhall not likewiſe the markes of the Beaſt bee <hi>myſtically</hi> interpreted, of ſome ſuperſtitious rites
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17704:13"/>
or ceremonies, taken in hand or forehead? whereby ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection is profeſſed vnto the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> as to a ſacred <hi>Maieſtie</hi> vpon earth?</p>
                  <p>Thus by Gods gracious aſſiſtance, it reſteth proued, what the <hi>Beaſt</hi> is, to weet, a flagitious ſtate of Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſet vp againſt that of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> though pretended to bee the very ſame with that of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, as hereafter wee ſhall proue more fully. It reſteth alſo proued, what the <hi>Image</hi> of this <hi>Beaſt</hi> is, A ſcelerate and idolatrous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of the ſame, either by a like ſubordinate ſtate vnto it; or elſe by ſome other ſimiltudinary meanes, as is aboue expreſſed: and laſtly it reſteth proued, what the taking of the beaſts marke in the hand or forehead is, to weet, An impious acknowledgement, and adoration of the Antichriſtian State, by ſome ſuperſtitious rite, <hi>ſaker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> or <hi>ceremony</hi> taken in hand or forehead: and yet the greateſt difficultie and obſcurity remaines behind; which now comes to bee cleared and opened by vs: to weet, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what forme of Gouernment now vpon earth, may we faſten ſo grieuous an imputation? Is this wicked State and forme of Gouernment, yet come or are we to looke for it? O thou innocent <hi>Lion, who haſt the key of Dauid, who openeſt</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Authors prayer.</note> 
                     <hi>and no man ſhutteth,</hi> vnſeale vnto vs the ſecret of this thy ſacred myſterie!</p>
                  <p>For the cleering of this great difficulty, wee muſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe<note place="margin">Firſt ſuppoſition.</note> theſe things. Firſt, that this <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> State, typed by the Beaſt and the Image of the Beaſt, together with the adoration thereof, and the flagitious ſubiection yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereunto (typed by the taking of the marke of<note place="margin">The ſtate of the Beaſt, can be no meere politick Ciuil State or Empire.</note> the beaſt, and of the name or the number of the name of the beaſt in hand or on forehead) cannot iuſtly bee applied to any ciuil forme of Gouernment, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of any ciuill ſubiection yeelded thereunto: No, no, it is moſt certaine, that all ſuch ciuill States are the <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God;</hi> and that all ciuill ſubiection (out of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) yeelded to ſuch powers, is expreſly required by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17704:14"/>
God; yea ſo ſtricktly, that whoſoeuer ſhall deny the ſame,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> they ſhall thereby purchaſe to themſelues <hi>condemnation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, I ſuppoſe, that the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> State heere<note place="margin">2. Suppoſ. The State of the Beaſt a p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>etended ſacred State.</note> condemned, is a State pretending to bee diuinely Sacred (as <hi>Chriſts</hi> one <hi>Rod</hi> and <hi>Scepter</hi>) ſo powerfull, that it ſhall preſume to change lawes and times; ſo arrogantly ſacred, that it ſhall vndertake to inſtitute other rites and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, then thoſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath appointed, for the aboliſhing of ſin, and for ſanctifying of the Soule: A State challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging<note place="margin">Matt. 24. 6. Apoc. 13. 15.</note> to bee acknowledged, by a religious ſupernaturall faith; and by diuine worſhip to bee honoured, and this ſo ſtrictly (in the very name of <hi>Chriſt</hi>) that whoſoeuer ſhall refuſe to doe the ſame, muſt be deſtroyed.</p>
                  <p>Hereout, I thirdly ſuppoſe; that the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> State<note place="margin">3. Suppoſ.</note> typed, ſhall in all arrogancie preſume to exerciſe her pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er<note place="margin">The State of the Beaſt ſhall exact ſupernaturall faith and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended State ouer the conſciences of men. 4. Suppoſ.</note> ouer the ſoules &amp; conſciences of men, requiring from them a diuine faith in the profeſſion of her power; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting from them an abſolute obedience out of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to her <hi>Authoritie;</hi> to admit of all her Rites, all her Lawes, euen as the very Rites and Lawes of <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>In the fourth place I ſuppoſe; that the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> State, ſhall not onely pretend a ſpirituall power (typed by<note place="margin">The State of the Beast a M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy vp<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n diuine, p<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tence.</note> 
                     <hi>the hornes of a Lamb</hi>) but alſo an vniuerſall (direct or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct) temporall power: <hi>For he ſhall ſpeake like the Dragon,</hi> and conſequently ſhal with infinite afflictions vexe thoſe, who adhering to the doctrines of the Preachers, typed by<note place="margin">Apoc. 14. 9. 10.</note> the three <hi>Angels,</hi> are onely and ſolely for the Faith of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> againſt his ſuperſtitious rites; are onely and ſolely for obedience to the Commandements of <hi>God,</hi> againſt his humane traditions, are onely and ſolely for the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of <hi>God,</hi> againſt the adoration and worſhip of any creatures, againſt all his enforced <hi>Thelo-threskies,</hi> and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhips. On the contrary he ſhall inrich with wealth and treaſury; increaſe in glory and honor; all thoſe, who ſhall fall downe, adore and worſhip him, and his State.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:17704:14"/>Theſe moſt true ſuppoſitions (which with an infinitie of teſtimonies, and reaſons might be confirmed) being<note place="margin">The Papall State the State of the Beaſt.</note> carefully preobſerued: I doe in the feare of God, and out of the confidence of a good conſcience conſtantly lay this imputation, vpon the preſent ſtate and gouernment of the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> affirmimg his State and Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to be that flagitious State, which is here typed forth by the Beaſt, and by the Image of the Beaſt: And ſo here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by<note place="margin">Articles agreed on by the Synod of Biſhops, and the Conuocation.</note> I demonſtrate, how true that is which wee haue (and in the defence whereof I haue partly meditated this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument) in our <hi>Articles of the Church of England,</hi> That the <hi>Biſhop of Rome hath no iuriſdiction in the Realme of England:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 68.</note> For if his <hi>State</hi> bee <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> and of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> (as his <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> alſo moſt truely in his <hi>Premonions to Chriſtian Princes</hi>) then it will follow vnuoidably, that all his chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge for iuriſdiction within the <hi>Realme</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> is ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancie and preſumption. This my imputation I will not endeauour to proue, by enumetating an infinitie of their blaſphemous ſuperſtitions and lawes againſt the Maieſtie of <hi>God,</hi> the glory of his <hi>Sonne,</hi> and the honour of his <hi>Tabernacle</hi> (the true vniuerſall <hi>Catholike Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi>) but I will onely doe it (<hi>Gods</hi> holy Spiiit enabling mee) by certaine generall demonſtrations, drawne from the conſideration of the very proper conditions of the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> State it ſelfe; partly laid downe in my former ſuppoſitions, but moſt fully in the Booke of <hi>God,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto for breuitie ſake I will only point my religious Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
                  <p>Firſt then I argue thus: The State of the Beaſt, muſt<note place="margin">F<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rſt reaſon.</note> bee a State vpon earth, pretending to bee for <hi>Chriſt</hi> 
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Matt. 24. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in the name of Chriſt,</hi> and bearing pretenſedly the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <note n="b" place="margin">Apoc. 13. 11. 2. Theſſal. 2. <hi>A vanity in</hi> Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine, <hi>affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt ſhall deny Chriſt.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>hornes of the Lamb,</hi> though in truth it ſhall <hi>ſpeake like the Dragon:</hi> Againe, this State muſt bee not a procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med impudencie of <hi>Iniquitie;</hi> but it muſt bee a <hi>myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> a pretenſed ſemblance of <hi>Chriſtian Sanctitie:</hi> A State ſo full of ſubtiltie, and pretending the name of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17704:15"/>
                     <hi>Chriſt,</hi> euen to the doing of miracles, and ſuch miracles<note place="margin">Matth. 24. 2. Theſſ. 2. Hi<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>r. orat. in Aux<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nt. Hiero. Epiſt <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1 q. ad algaſ. Oec<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>men. Theophil. in 2. Theſſ. 2 &amp; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt ibid alij. <hi>See</hi> Remes An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notat in 2. Theſ. 2. annotat. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>that the very Elect ſhall bee in danger to be ſeduced.</hi> It muſt alſo be a State ruling and ſitting in the <hi>Temple of God,</hi> that is in the viſible Churches of God (ſo certaine of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) pretending therein (in Gods ſtead) to haue power ouer the verie ſoules and conſciences of the faithfull: yea, and therein to haue (in <hi>Gods</hi> ſtead) a power diſpenſatiue ouer all the Lawes of <hi>God;</hi> ouer all powers ordained by <hi>God;</hi> ouer all that is ſacred <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>all Maieſtie</hi> whatſoeuer. And are not theſe, and euery of theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, moſt properly appliable to the preſent <hi>Papall Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> State? onely and ſolely to the <hi>Papall</hi> State? It alone pretends to w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>are the <hi>Lambs hornes,</hi> and to bee an abſolute <hi>Vice-gerencie</hi> for <hi>Chriſt:</hi> It alone requires that her Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie<note place="margin">The Papall State pretinded to be Chriſts own ſtate.</note> and power<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> bee beleeued (vnder neceſſitie of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) with ſupernaturall faith: Shee alone, pretends to ſit (that is to rule) in the temple of <hi>God,</hi> that is the whole vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rch</hi> of <hi>God:</hi> to rule (I ſay) the ſame with a <hi>rod of Iron and Direction.</hi> Shee alone, works in ſo powerfull and ſubtill a manner (pretending <hi>Chriſts</hi> power) miracles done in his name, that thereby ſhee (drawing to her band <hi>a whole multitude of Inhabitants of the earth) hazards the ſoules of the very elect; ſo that they are in danger to be ſeduced.</hi> Thus our firſt proofe; and yet here I muſt not omit to note, that though the <hi>Papall</hi> State, pretends the <hi>Lambs hornes;</hi> that is, to be <hi>Christs</hi> abſolute and ſole <hi>Vice-gerent:</hi> yet notwithſtanding, it ſpeakes like the <hi>Dragon;</hi> How, ſpeakes like the Dragon? For that it perſecutes with Sword, Fire, and Fagot (as the <hi>Dragon</hi> did) all thoſe who cleaue only to the Lambe; for their ſaluation hoping on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">Reuel. 13. 11.</note> vpon the Lambes merites; for their direction both in faith and manners, reſting onely on the Lambes Word.<note place="margin">The Roman Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers like the old Emperours In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of the Dragon,</note> And are not theſe the very things, for which the <hi>Dragon</hi> perſecuted the firſt Chriſtians in the <hi>Roman Emperours?</hi> and doth hee not now perſecute vs for the very ſame in the <hi>Roman Fathers Pope-Emperours?</hi> It is the teſtimony
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17704:15"/>
of <hi>Ieſus:</hi> Ieſus onely, Ieſus ſolely, which the <hi>Dragon</hi> perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by the old Emperours; and it is the ſame teſtimony of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> which the Dragon perſecuteth in theſe Roman Fathers: The <hi>Roman Emperours,</hi> would not haue <hi>Ieſus</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to be honoured, againſt their <hi>Idoll-Gods;</hi> And theſe Holy <hi>Fathers,</hi> will not haue <hi>Ieſus</hi> alone, to bee acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged &amp; beleeued to ſaluation without their Godlings, nor to bee onely heard for direction, without their Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. Becauſe we will acknowledge nothing, nor will beleeue no other neceſſary for ſaluation, but Ieſus, onely Ieſus: This is that very teſtimony, againſt which the <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon</hi> now ſpeaketh in the <hi>Roman</hi> Fathers, and perſecuteth in vs, with the extremitie of Fire, Sword, and Faggot.</p>
                  <p>My ſecond reaſon I frame thus; The ſtate <hi>Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Second Reaſon.</note> wil require, to be adored of all the <hi>Inhabitants of Earth;</hi> not with ciuill and humane adoration onely; but with a<note place="margin">Apoc. 13. 15. 16</note> ſupernaturall adoration, with a ſoule-Reuerence due to it, as to an earthly <hi>God.</hi> But this the <hi>Papall</hi> State moſt exactly<note place="margin">Adoration giuen to the Papall State, as to an <hi>Numen</hi> and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth</note> doth require; and as yet no other State euer required the ſame; neither can, or ſhall any other (with fire and fag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got) more rigorouſly require the ſame, then the <hi>Papall</hi> State, now doth require it: It followeth then, that the <hi>Papall</hi> State, is that very State which is here typed by the <hi>Beaſt:</hi> That the <hi>Papall</hi> State requireth ſuch a ſoule-ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and ſupernaturall obedience, as due to an earthly <hi>Deitie,</hi> it is more then moſt manifeſt: For, who hath not obſerued, that in a religious ſubiection to the <hi>Pope,</hi> and in a <hi>Soule-vnion</hi> with the <hi>Pope,</hi> conſiſteth the very life and<note place="margin">Wherein conſiſteth the life of the Papacy.</note> eſſence of the <hi>Papall</hi> State? Here hence it is, that it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted a high point of the <hi>Maieſty</hi> of that State (yea it is reputed as a partiall meanes to ſaluation) that the <hi>Pope</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth <hi>adorations</hi> and <hi>kiſſings of his feet,</hi> from all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full<note place="margin">An act of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to kiſſe the Popes feet.</note> of the world; and in their faith ought to receiue (at leſt in preparation of mind) from all the <hi>Inhabitants of the Earth.</hi> Loe, how that of the <hi>Prophet</hi> is accompliſhed, <hi>That</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Apoc. 13 4.</note> 
                     <hi>the whole earth admired after the Beaſt.</hi> This reaſon I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17704:16"/>
with the words of <hi>Odoard Guilliand, Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Caſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                     <note place="margin">Odoard. Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dus de Ciuili &amp; moral. Facult. lib. 14 cap. 3.</note> a Citie of <hi>Flaminia</hi> in <hi>Italy.</hi> This man in a certaine booke of his, dedicated to <hi>Clement</hi> the eighth, doth excellently deſcribe vnto vs, the Diuinitie and <hi>Godhead</hi> of their Holy Fathers the <hi>Popes. A Papa</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>tanquam à Capite in vniuerſum Eccleſiae corpus, hoc eſt in omnem Chriſtianan rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicam, ſpiritus influunt celeſtium gratiarum ſenſum fruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumque praeſtantes, &amp; efficacem motum ad ſempiternam beatidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, merito igitur Sanctiſſimus, &amp; Beatiſſimus appellatur, &amp; ab omnibus religionem Chriſtianam profitentibus, quaſi quidam Deus adoratur, &amp; colitur. From the Pope, as from the head, there doth flow into the whole body of the Church, that is into the whole Chriſtian common-wealth, certaine ſpirits of heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly graces, which doe yeeld both ſenſe and fruit, and efficacious</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Pope to be adored as a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aine God.</note> 
                     <hi>motion to euerlaſting happineſſe: worthily therefore, is hee called moſt Holy, and moſt Bleſſed, and of all thoſe who profeſſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, hee is to bee adored and worſhipped as a certaine God.</hi> Thus hee, and ſuch is the blaſphemous note and tune of diuers of them, flat oppoſite to that confeſſion of the Saints in the Reuelations: <hi>Saluation commeth from our God, that ſitteth vpon the Throne, and from the Lamb.</hi> And ſhall<note place="margin">Apoc 7. 10.</note> wee deſire more to lay open the blaſphemous preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that <hi>State?</hi> or ſhall wee dare to affirme, that ſuch <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirers</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Reuel. 13. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>after the Beaſt,</hi> that ſitteth in the Temple of God, ſhewing himſelfe <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> as if hee were God are in the<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2. 4.</note> ſtate of ſaluation) if they bee wilfully obſtinate and reluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant againſt the truth ſufficiently propoſed vnto them?</p>
                  <p>In the third place I reaſon thus; The <hi>Antichriſtian</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Third Reaſon.</note> ſtate, is that very Gouernment, againſt which in the very height of her pride and preſumptions, certaine zealous and <hi>Godly</hi> Preachers (foreſignified by the three <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Reuel. 14. 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11.</note> 
                     <hi>flying through the middeſt of Heauen, and hauing the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The preaching of the three Angells accompliſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Papall State.</note> 
                     <hi>Goſpel</hi>) were to oppoſe themſelues, by preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>feare and worſhip of God alone, and keeping of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements,</hi> and conſequently, were to beat downe all manner of <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Wilworſhip</hi> reared vp againſt the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17704:16"/>
ſame: were againe in the ſecond place, to ſound out the <hi>ruine and deſolation of that State;</hi> and conſequently, were to check the inſolent confidence of her followers and <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirers,</hi> glorying in her euer <hi>infallibility</hi> and indefectibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: And laſtly, were in the third place, to dehort from all manner of communion with that ſtate; and agreeing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were to teach all true <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to deteſt the <hi>marks</hi> and <hi>characters</hi> of that State. And is not this <hi>the very ſelfe-Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Papall State perſecuteth the Preachers typed by the three An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</note> 
                     <hi>of Reformation,</hi> which the <hi>Paſtours</hi> and <hi>Doctours</hi> of the Reformed <hi>Churches</hi> doe now ſound out againſt the <hi>Papall</hi> State, yea and (according to the prediction of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets) to the begun ruine of the <hi>Papall</hi> State? This reaſon<note place="margin">Apoc. 14. 2.</note> may bee confirmed, if with all wee conſider, that euen as it is foretold in the Reuelation, the ſame. Chapter; The <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian</hi> State, would conceiue ſo great rage againſt the ſaid Preachers (typed by the three <hi>Angells</hi>) for ſuch their preaching and doctrines, that thereupon it would raiſe,<note place="margin">Reue. 14. 12, 13</note> or cauſe to bee raiſed againſt them moſt fearefull perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; perſecutions ſo great and ſo manifold, that the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>God</hi> though it meet to prearme his choſen againſt the ſame, with theſe and ſuch like comfortable inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: <hi>Here is the faith and patience of Saints; here are thoſe, who keepe the commandements of God, and the faith of Ieſus. Bleſſed are thoſe, who dye in the Lord, who dye for the Lord; From henceforth ſaith the Spirit, they ſhall reſt from their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Reuel. 2. 29.</note> Thus there; In which moſt comfortable inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, doth not the Spirit of <hi>God</hi> manifeſtly premoniſh, and prearme vs of theſe times againſt the Pope? <hi>Heare all yee, that haue eares to heare, what the Spirit of God ſaith to the Churches.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Paſtors of the Reformed churches ſuffered from the Pope, according as by Gods Spirit it hath bin foretold</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>For, is not this the very thing, which is now, and hath formerly beene acted in the world? Doe not the <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Doctors</hi> of the Reformed <hi>Churches,</hi> and other faithfull, ſuffer for this very cauſe? for that they ſound out pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely the doctrines of the three <hi>Angells;</hi> the <hi>Euerlaſting Goſpell?</hi> of the feare of <hi>God</hi> alone? of the ruine and fall of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17704:17"/>
                     <hi>Babylon?</hi> of the <hi>State</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt?</hi> and againſt the taking of the markes and characters of the Beaſt in hand or on forehead? and from whom, or by whoſe meanes do they ſuffer for ſuch things, but from the <hi>Papall</hi> ſtate? What In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries are made after them? What hideous Inquiſitions are reared for them? What <hi>Croſſe-warres</hi> haue beene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed againſt them? Aske our Fathers of old in <hi>France, Italy, Germany, Spaine, England, Denmarke, Scotland, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gandy,</hi> and where not? Our Aduerſaries the <hi>Pontificians</hi> cannot deny this, it being the very deſire of their Fathers and of their owne ſoules. Let it then reſt proued, that the principle prophecie againſt the State of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> being accompliſhed in the <hi>Papall</hi> State, that the <hi>Papall</hi> State is the very State of the <hi>Beaſt.</hi> And ſo I adioyne a fourth reaſon thus.</p>
                  <p>That is, the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> State (typed by the Beaſt, and<note place="margin">Fourth Reaſon.</note> the Image thereof) or typed by the ſeuen and eight<note place="margin">Auguſt. 20. de Ciuit c. 19. Hier. ad Algaſ. queſt. 11. in Dan &amp; ad Gerontia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de monogamia. Tertul. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrect. carnis Cir. catech. 15. Chryſ. Ambroſ. Theophil. Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cume Primaſi in 2. Theſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 2. <hi>The Papall State hath done out of the way tho Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empire. See</hi> gloſ in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non ſi Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tori Radeuic. de geſtis Friderici. Sidon. l. 11. de regno Itali<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> heads thereof) which was in the very gouernment of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe, to ſucceed the <hi>Roman</hi> temporall <hi>Empire:</hi> So diuers of the Ancient Fathers, <hi>Auſten, Hierom, Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Tertullian,</hi> with others haue affirmed: vnto which <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian</hi> State alſo, <hi>ten Kings</hi> (a number certaine for an vncertaine) ſpringing out of the ruines of the <hi>Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, were for a time to giue their powers</hi> (for the honouring and ſupporting of her) and yet <hi>afterwards</hi> (forſaking her) <hi>would</hi> bend their forces againſt her <hi>(God, putting the ſame into their hearts) to make her deſolate, and conſume her with fire.</hi> And is not this the very <hi>Papall</hi> State it ſelfe, ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the Gouernment and Empire ouer <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Temporall Empire?</hi> For in <hi>Rome</hi> who knowes not, that it is reputed no leſſe crime then <hi>le-ſo-Sanctitie,</hi> to affirme the Emperours (that are now) to haue ought to doe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, independently from the <hi>Pope?</hi> or that they haue any <hi>Emperiall Soueraignty</hi> ouer <hi>Rome:</hi> no, no, in the faith of the <hi>Pope</hi> and his, <hi>Imperator Preſens,</hi> the preſent Emperour is but <hi>Homo ligius Papae: A liege deuout ſeruant to the Pope.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17704:17"/>
to too apparent it is, that thoſe <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> into which the temporal <hi>Roman</hi> Empire (vpon her ruine) was diuided, did (the <hi>Dragon</hi> putting the ſame into their hearts) yeeld and ſubmit their powers and crownes vnto the <hi>Papall</hi> State, for the ſupport of the ſame: And is it not moſt manifeſt, that the ſaid <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Kingdomes (God put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſame into their hearts)</hi> haue alreadie begun to hate the <hi>Papall</hi> State, to make it deſolate, &amp; to conſume it with the fire of the zeale of Gods glory and truth, God grant they continue the ſame vnto the end: but ſhould any States or Kingdomes which haue begun in the ſpirit de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to the fleſh, yet ſhall they neuer bee able to make fruſtrate and void <hi>Gods</hi> infallible and ineuitable decree, of the vtter ruine and fall of the <hi>Autichriſtian</hi> State, euen as of <hi>a milſtone caſt into the bottomleſſe Sea,</hi> whereof there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth<note place="margin">Apoc. 17.</note> neither token nor memory: And ſo I adde a fifth proofe.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> State, is that State which was to haue<note place="margin">Fifth Reaſon.</note> her Sea, and to reſide in <hi>myſticall Babylon;</hi> myſticall <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> that Great <hi>Citie which is ſituated vpon ſeuen Hills:</hi> that<note place="margin">Reu. 17. 9. 4, 18, &amp;c.</note> Citie, <hi>which in S. Iohns time had rule</hi> and command <hi>ouer the Kings of the Earth;</hi> that Citie which was to be a whore<note place="margin">The Antichriſtian Throne in Rome.</note> and <hi>Apostata</hi> from her firſt faith, by ſuperadding many doctrines of deuills, and errors of wicked ſpirits; and yet<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.</note> was inſolently to glory of her euer-in errabilitie, and that ſhee ſhould ſee no <hi>widow-hood:</hi> that Citie, which was to<note place="margin">Reuel. 17. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>make drunke with the cup of her abominations</hi> (pretending to bee the ſole mother of Chriſtianitie) <hi>all the Kings and</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibid. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>Kingdomes of the Earth;</hi> that Citie which was to be ruddy <hi>with the bloud of Saints,</hi> thoſe Saints which were to ſuffer <hi>for the teſtimony of Ieſus,</hi> I interpret for the ſole faith of Ieſus, as the onely meanes of ſaluation. That <hi>Citie</hi> which<note place="margin">Ibid. 5.</note> was to haue the name <hi>Myſtery written in her forehead,</hi> full of myſteries; profeſſing myſteries; making myſteries: That Citie which was with honour, riches, and glory to inrich and make glorious all her Louers and Admirers,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17704:18"/>
the <hi>Inhabitants of the Earth.</hi> And are not all theſe things moſt punctually accompliſhed in the <hi>Papall</hi> State? I need not to repeat nor to make any particular application; but I ſay againe, and againe, are not all theſe things, with all other ſuch like (fore prophecied by the Spirit of God, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Antichriſtian State) fulfilled and accompliſhed in the <hi>Papall</hi> State, which hath its reſidence in <hi>Rome,</hi> its Throne and See in <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Some of our Aduerſaries (that ſo wee may anſwere an<note place="margin">A vaine obiection</note> obiection by the way) doe againſt this reaſon, pretend a very idle euaſion; they acknowledge, that <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall bee the Seat of the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> State, and of the <hi>Beaſt;</hi> but <hi>Rome Ethnike,</hi> ſay they, not <hi>Rome</hi> Chriſtian; <hi>Rome</hi> as it was before the daies of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> but not <hi>Rome</hi> as it is now in theſe our times. O the vanitie of this anſwere, <hi>Rome</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Anſwere.</note> 
                     <hi>Ethnike,</hi> as it was before the time of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> is to be the Throne of the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> State, and Seat of the <hi>Beaſt?</hi> and yet in their owne opinions <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is not to come vntill a verie ſhort time before the conſummation of the world, and then alſo his reigne (in their opinions) is to be onely of three yeeres and a halfe continuance. O that theſe wiſe Sages would informe vs, how this their Inerra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Infallible <hi>Papall</hi> See (ſo they glory) ſhall become <hi>Ethnike</hi> and <hi>Heatheniſh?</hi> By what precurſour of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhall it bee ſo made <hi>Heatheniſh?</hi> for the entertaining of the Great <hi>Antichriſt?</hi> ſhall <hi>Antichriſt</hi> himſelfe make it <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh</hi> and <hi>Ethnike?</hi> ſhall he reare vp the adoration of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Gods</hi> (the proper character and badge of <hi>Heatheniſme,</hi>) that, they cannot ſay, for they profeſſe (vainely) that <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt</hi> ſhall ſuppreſſe all manner of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> hee cannot then be in their iudgements the Author of <hi>Heaniſh Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try;</hi> vaine then and moſt vaine is their pretended reaſon.</p>
                  <p>Againe, like vaine is their anſwere, when they pretend,<note place="margin">A ſecond euaſion.</note> that the Beaſt which ſhall ſit at <hi>Rome,</hi> is not the ſame, with that <hi>Beaſt</hi> which ariſes out of the <hi>Sea, hauing ſeuen heads</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Apoc. 13.</note>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:17704:18"/>
                     <hi>and ten hornes.</hi> For doe they not all confeſſe, that both<note place="margin">Anſwere.</note> Beaſts doe type vnto vs <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> yea the Great <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt?</hi> which Antichriſt, in all their iudgements ſhall bee ſo indiuidually, one onely man, that herehence they think they haue an inuincible buckler of defence againſt vs, that their <hi>Popes</hi> are not <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> nor the Beaſt; for that they are not one only man, but many, yea very many, a whole Generatinn of men: how then can they auoid, but that it is one and the ſame <hi>Antichriſt</hi> which is typed by both the <hi>Beaſts?</hi> for if <hi>Antichriſt</hi> typed by both, be indiuidually one, then of neceſſitie one and the ſame <hi>State</hi> is typed and ſignified by both the <hi>Beaſts:</hi> And if <hi>Antichriſt</hi> (typed by the one Beaſt) ſit at <hi>Rome;</hi> hee cannot alſo ſit at <hi>Babylon,</hi> vnleſſe it bee by turnes; or that the faire Beaſt bee diuided into two parts, the one to haue his Throne at <hi>Rome,</hi> the other to haue his ſeat at <hi>Babylon:</hi> Let it then thus reſt proued, that the preſent <hi>Papall</hi> ſtate, is the very <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> ſtate, typed by the <hi>Beaſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This imputation, which is ſo grieuous and heauie; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer<note place="margin">Diuers learned Authors of the Papiſts Church, haue reputed the Papall State An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian and of the Beaſt.</note> it may to ſome as halt betwixt God and <hi>Baal</hi> (for many ſuch medleys theſe times haue) ſeeme iniurious; yet is it not much more, then that, which ſome ingenious profeſſours (of diuers points of Poperie) haue propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally and couertly heretofore deliuered, to the euerlaſting confuſion of that State: <hi>Bernard</hi> was not farre from the ſight hereof (for to him in part <hi>Gods</hi> ſpirit had reueal<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d this truth) when as, in reſpect of the infinite abuſes of the <hi>Papall</hi> ſtate, hee cries out that the <hi>Churches</hi> of his times,<note place="margin">Bernard l. 4. de conſiderat.</note> were <hi>rather folds for deuills then for ſheep;</hi> and in his ſermon vpon the conuerſion of <hi>S. Paul,</hi> hee complaineth; that<note place="margin">Ser. 1. in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. S. Pauli.</note> 
                     <hi>the whole Church of Chriſtianity</hi> (ſo I interpret) <hi>ſeemed to haue conſpired againſt God;</hi> yea ſo conſpired, that in regard<note place="margin">In Pſal. qui ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitat. Pſal. 91.</note> thereof, hee is bold thus to pronounce elſewhere: <hi>It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>that the Man of Sin, and Sonne of Perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on bee reuealed; not onely the day, but the very noone-deuill; which is not onely transformed into an Angell of light, but is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17704:19"/>
extolled aboue all that is called God, or that is worſhipped.</hi> Thus hee; where I cannot but note, that <hi>Bernard</hi> vſing the phraſe of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> (in regard of the exceſſe of impieties and abominable iniquities) was ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bee reuealed, ſhortly to bee reuealed; I cannot, I ſay, but note how that <hi>Bernard</hi> did think, that Antichriſt and his ſtate, did then worke powerfully and rage tirannouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and where if not there, in that, rather <hi>Court</hi> then<note place="margin">Ber. Epiſt. 235. ad Curia Roma.</note> 
                     <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> vnto which <hi>Bernard</hi> writing, dareth to proclaime thus. <hi>In the very houſe of God, wee obſerue things horrible;</hi> Theſe horrible things, which <hi>Bernard</hi> obſerued in <hi>Rome,</hi> to vs is reuealed to be the very <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> himſelfe, and of his Admirers that worſhip him.</p>
                  <p>Was <hi>Peter de Aliaco,</hi> that venerable <hi>Prelate</hi> of <hi>Cambray,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Aliac. de Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat. Eccleſ. ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat. Conc. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</note> farre from the ſight of this truth, whereas hee dares to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that the <hi>Church in his dayes, was come to that paſſe, that it deſerued to bee ruled onely by Reprobates?</hi> Was <hi>Gerſon</hi> farre off, when as he confidently affirmes, that (through <hi>papall</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gerſo. to. 1. de Conc. Gener. &amp; vnius obed. q. 5.</note> abuſes) the Churches of his times, were come to be, <hi>totas brutales, carnales, monſtroſas, nihil ſapientes; Brutiſh, carnall, monſtrous, vnderſtanding naught.</hi> I interpret <hi>naught,</hi> that was good or pious. Was <hi>Ioannes Sarisburienſis</hi> farre off,<note place="margin">Policatat. l. 6. c. 17.</note> when as hee profeſſeth that the Church of <hi>Rome, was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a den of theeues; the ſecret of the Sanctuary was become a Stew;</hi> yea, and that <hi>the Church of Rome was become a ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Apud Auentinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
                     <hi>to all?</hi> I paſſe by many others, yea Synods of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh <hi>Biſhops</hi> in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> in plaine wordes ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Holy Father <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> How downe-right is <hi>Bernard Morlanenſis,</hi> calling the Pope, <hi>Ipſum Regem Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Morlane de co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. num. 3. apud vſherum.</note> 
                     <hi>the very King of Babylon;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Heu ſua propria deputat omnia Rex Babylonis,</l>
                     <l>Out alac the King of Babylon reputes all for his owne.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>A complaint which <hi>Bernard</hi> vſed againſt the Holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.<note place="margin">Lib. do conſid. clariſsime.</note> But howſoeuer I paſſe by the teſtimony of theſe, and diuers others, yet I may not omit the ingenuous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of a venerable <hi>Prieſt</hi> of <hi>Burgandie.</hi> This man, doth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17704:19"/>
ſo largely and punctually point out, and declare vnto vs, the Antichriſtianitie of the <hi>Popiſh Church,</hi> that hee ſeemes to haue had that reuealed vnto him, which hee durſt not<note place="margin">Circ. An. 1200.</note> commend to writing; euen that very truth of Papall An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtianitie, which to vs is made ſo manifeſt: <hi>Intuere,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Honor. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodunenſis. in dialog.—in Auctau<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Bib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lioth. Pat. ad Calcem. Edit. Pariſ. 1610. collect. ex vſhero.</note> ſaith he, <hi>Principes &amp; ludices, in his poſita eſt Beſtiae Sedes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Princes and Iudges, in them is ſet the Seat of the beaſt; They are euer intent to euill, euer vnſatiably oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied in buſineſſes of Iniquitie: They doe not onely themſelues ſcelerately; but they teach others ſo to do: They ſell holy things, they buy crimes, and their whole indeuour is, that they may not goe alone to hell. verte te ad Clerum &amp; videbis in eis, beſtia tentorium, &amp;c. Turne thy ſelfe to the Clergie, and in them thou</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A notable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the ſtate of the Beaſt in the Papacie.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhalt ſee, the very tent of the beaſt; They neglect the ſeruice of God, they ſtudie earthly gaine; their Prieſthood they pollute by vncleanneſſe, the people they ſeduce by hypocriſie, they deny God by their wicked liues, they ſhake off all Scriptures, which ſerue for ſaluation; by all meanes they ſet themſelues as ſnares, and a ruine to the people, whom (being blind themſelues) they lead blind to deſtruction. Contemplure &amp; Monachorum Concilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bula, &amp; videbis in eis beſtiae tabernacula, &amp;c. Contemplate the Conuents or Conuenticles of Monkes, and in them thou ſhalt ſee the Tabernacles of the beaſt, by their fained profeſſion (deriding God) they prouoke his wrath; by their wicked life and manners they trample downe all regular diſcipline; by their habite they deceiue the world, and being themſelues deceiued, they deceiue many: they are intangled with worldly buſineſſes, being ſlugiſh in the ſeruice of God: many of the<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> are giuen and addicted to luxury and gluttony; ſome of them rot in the durt and filth of vncleanneſſe. Aſpice etiam habitaculae monialium, &amp; in eis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes beſtiae preparatum thalamum, &amp;c. Looke vpon the habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Nuns; and in them, ſee a bride-chamber prepared for the beaſt: Theſe from their tender age learne impudency, to the increaſe of their damnation, they draw vnto them many compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; they hasten to bee couered with Vailes, that by ſuch a meanes they may let looſe the bridles of luxury; they doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17704:20"/>
themſelues, in a worſe ſort then any fornicators, and as an vnſatiable gulfe, they are neuer filled with the dung of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe; Theſe doe enſnare the ſoules of young men, and then they reioyce when they haue enſnared many; and ſhee reputes her ſelfe worthy of the Palme of victory, who excelleth in villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. Verte te ad plebem reliquam, &amp; in ea videbis beſtiae effigiem, &amp;c. Turne thee to the other of the people, and in them thou ſhalt ſee the very ſhape of the beaſt: Prieſts they deſpiſe, they contemne to heare ought of God, they lead their whole life in pride, boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and vanitie, and are reprobate to euery good worke. Alſo the vnlearned multitude hath the very Idoll of the beaſt, the true God they haue not knowne, but with all deuotion they ſerue the God of their belly; they are carried with various deſires of the fleſh, and in euery reſpect they lead a beaſt-like life.</hi> Thus hee (with more to like purpoſe) deſcribeth the beaſtiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Papall State. Can you deſire more, or will you require more?</p>
                  <p>And thus haue wee, by euidencie of Scripture, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther venerable authoritie, faſtned vnuoydably the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian</hi> State and Gouernment vpon the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and his purpured brethren; and thereby alſo haue I ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the vanitie of his ambitious <hi>claime</hi> of ſupremacie ouer this <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Kingdome;</hi> for no one point is more <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian</hi> in him, then his vſurped claime of <hi>ſupremacy;</hi> and for my part, I am of opinion (and I dare vndertake very probably to confirme the ſame) that whoſoeuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies the <hi>Pope</hi> to be <hi>Antichriſt</hi> (that <hi>ſonne of perdition, who</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>ſitteth in the Temple of God</hi>) may iuſtly bee ſuſpected, to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour his moſt ambitious claime of ſupremacie; this I meane of thoſe who vnderſtand themſelues, and the extent of theſe termes; the Papall State, Antichriſtianity, Papall Supremacie, Roman Monarchy, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>For further confirmation, of this our principall point in hand, I could produce more proofe, or Grounds and Principles of reaſons, from out of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles to the <hi>Theſſalonians;</hi> to <hi>Timothy</hi> and to the <hi>Romans;</hi> yea, from
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17704:20"/>
out of the Epiſtles of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> and holy <hi>Iude;</hi> and from out of <hi>Daniel:</hi> more, there are very few Prophecies in the Scriptures of <hi>God,</hi> or in the approued predictions of any of the ſeruants of <hi>God</hi> (concerning <hi>Antichriſt</hi> and his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment) which may not moſt probably (if not euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) bee ſettled vpon the <hi>Papall</hi> State, either the <hi>head</hi> or members thereof: but that which hath beene deliuered, may ſuffice for the euidencie of this truth, eſpecially with<note place="margin">How Neutrali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers betray Gods truth.</note> ſincere profeſſours: thoſe I meane which are not <hi>Neutra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizers</hi> (if any ſuch heare mee this day) <hi>Neutralizers,</hi> I ſay, or <hi>Interim-iſts;</hi> ſuch as dare ſecretly mutter and muſſitate; <hi>Rome</hi> and the Reformed <hi>Churches</hi> agree in the ſubſtance of Religion, that there is no fundamentall difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them and vs; and againe that they teach no <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies;</hi> ſo that they altogether with vs make vp but one my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall body of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> O the vanitie of theſe men! againſt the Spirit of <hi>God,</hi> thus to dreame of the vniting of <hi>Sion</hi> and <hi>Babylon;</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Hieruſalem;</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt;</hi> of <hi>light,</hi> and <hi>darkneſſe;</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Beliall:</hi> The<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.</note> Spirit of <hi>God</hi> hath foretold, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall in <hi>the brightnes of his comming, by the Spirit of his mouth,</hi> (that is, by the preaching of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> in the dayes of reformation, when that of the Reuelation ſhall bee accompliſhed, <hi>Oportet te iterum, &amp;c. Thou must againe prophecie to Nations, Peoples,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Apoc. 10. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>Tongues, and many Kings.</hi>) the Spirit of <hi>God</hi> hath (I ſay) foretold, that <hi>Antichriſt ſhall bee diſſipated and ruinated, by</hi>
                     <note place="margin">No vnion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the State of the Beast and true Chriſtianity.</note> 
                     <hi>the brightneſſe of his comming, and the Spirit of his mouth:</hi> and yet theſe men dare dreame of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> vnion, and brotherly conſociation betwixt thoſe, whom the Spirit of <hi>God</hi> doth thus diſunite and diſſociate; here, by a perfect hate, diuiding each from other, and in the world to come by caſting the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and his <hi>Admirers,</hi> into the lake of <hi>euer burning fire and brimſtone;</hi> and by taking vp to the ſupper and ioyes of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> thoſe, who haue here hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily followed the <hi>Lamb</hi> in all things, and haue alſo ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the teſtimonie of <hi>Ieſus</hi> the Lamb.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:17704:21"/>Now come we to declare, how the <hi>Papall</hi> State compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth all her followers, to take certaine impious markes in <hi>their hands,</hi> and likewiſe on their <hi>foreheads:</hi> without which they may not bee allowed, <hi>to buy or ſell,</hi> in that State.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>If any one receiue the marke of the Beaſt, either in his hand or in his forehead.</head>
                  <p>FOr declaration of this point (according to my vſe, and that I may the better bee vnderſtood) I ſuppoſe theſe<note place="margin">1. Suppoſ.</note> things: Firſt, that which I haue already euinced, by the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidencie of Reaſon, and the ioynt-conſent of Antiquitie,<note place="margin">The marke and character of the Beaſt, not to be taken for any beaſt-like marke, by inuſtion or by inciſion.</note> that theſe markes and <hi>Characters</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> are not to bee taken for any corporall ſignes, made either by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſtion of ſome hot-iron, or by the inciſion of ſome ſharpe inſtrument, in the hands, or vpon the foreheads of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts</hi> followers: no, no, the ſame is to bee vnderſtood of ſome flagitious <hi>myſticall ceremonies,</hi> taken in the hands, or on the foreheads: whereby the Takers are marked for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoted Seruants of the <hi>Beaſt.</hi> Secondly I ſuppoſe, that no<note place="margin">2. Suppoſ.</note> State or Gouernment, <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> or <hi>Hereticall, Arrian, Neſtorian, Pelagian,</hi> or of any other forme whatſoeuer, ſince the dayes of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> did euer cauſe and compell their followers to take any ſpeciall markes (ſpecializing their hereſies or infidelities) reall or ceremoniall in their hands, or on their foreheads (thereby to profeſſe a Soule-allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to the whole forme of their ſect and ſuperſtition) ſaue onely the <hi>Papall</hi> State.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly I ſuppoſe, that whereas it is ſaid that thoſe,<note place="margin">3. Suppoſ.</note> who would not receiue ſuch markes of the Beaſt, ſhould<note place="margin">Without the Beaſts marke no commerce.</note> haue no power, either to buy or to ſell in the <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> State; that the ſame muſt bee vnderſtood of a totall excluſion from all manner of communion and ſocietie in that wicked State: where that State doth preuaile and is not limited nor abridged, by the moderation of any Temporall power.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:17704:21"/>Fourthly, I ſuppoſe, that this totall excluſion from all<note place="margin">4. Suppoſ No buying, nor ſelling in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall State, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking of markes.</note> manner of buying and ſelling, is ſo punctually complea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the <hi>Papall</hi> State (yea in all <hi>Popiſh</hi> Kingdomes, where the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> is on foot) againſt all thoſe, who receiue not certaine markes of profeſſion and obedience from that State, that nothing can bee more aſſured, or more manifeſt.</p>
                  <p>Theſe things ſuppoſed, how manifeſt is it, that all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours of the <hi>Papall</hi> State, doe receiue in their hands, or on their foreheads, ſome ceremonious marke of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and profeſſion, which if they contemne to doe, they are reputed in that ſtate as <hi>Of-caſts,</hi> not to be admitted to<note place="margin">All in the Papall State receiue marks.</note> any manner of commerce and communion: Are they not all, or ought they not all (at leaſt in purpoſe of mind) to be anointed and marked on their foreheads, with <hi>oyle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated</hi> (I ſhould ſay execrated) by Papall Charmes? wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſame is become ſo ſacred, that the very preſence<note place="margin">Markes in the forehead.</note> and efficacie of the holy <hi>Ghoſt</hi> is ſaid, and by them is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued to bee therein: ſo ſacred, that the hands of thoſe, who are anointed therewith on their foreheads, may not preſume to touch the ſaid oyle, or their owne bare fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads ſo anointed; ſo ſacred, that the foreheads of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed,<note place="margin">Foreheads mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked muſt be bound with lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen fillets.</note> after the ſame inunction, are for certaine dayes to be couered with linnen bands faſtned thereunto, that by ſuch meanes the ſacred oyle may be defended from the iniury of wind, duſt, and weather, and may by ſuch conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance make better impreſſion, and pierce into the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head (ſuch is the vanitie of theſe fooleries, and impieties:) ſo ſacred, that the Popiſh <hi>Biſhop</hi> anointing the forehead, calls it and profeſſes it to be, <hi>Chriſma ſalutis, The very criſme</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Their manner &amp; forme of marking</note> 
                     <hi>of ſaluation, I ſigne thee</hi> (ſaith the Biſhop) <hi>with the ſigne of the Croſſe; and I confirme thee, with the criſme of ſaluation, in the name of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And may wee not here iuſtly exclaime againſt ſuch ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledgies?<note place="margin">A iuſt innection againſt marking vſed in Papacy.</note> thus to call a vile creature, the very <hi>Criſme</hi> of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17704:22"/>
ſaluation! O blaſphemy againſt the <hi>God</hi> of heauen! not <hi>Chriſt</hi> alone by his bloud, but the <hi>Beaſt</hi> by his char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Chriſme,</hi> doth and can giue ſaluation? O preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men, who without any command or inſtitution from <hi>God,</hi> dare thus ſacrilegiouſly preſume, to annexe the thrice ſacred name of the <hi>Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt,</hi> (and this in a ſacramentall manner for remiſſion of ſins)<note place="margin">The marks of the Papacie worthy to be execrated.</note> to a vile and meane creature! Who that hath eares to hear, eyes to ſee, and a heart to conceiue, doth not obſerue this flagitious cerermony, to bee an Antichriſtian marke ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the forehead? A marke, not onely becauſe by a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious and tranſeunt motion, ſigned by the thumb or finger on the forehead: not onely a marke, becauſe the <hi>Chriſme</hi> is to bee faſt bound to the forehead, ſo that if it were poſſible it might make ſome reall impreſſion in the fleſh: but a marke moſt properly, becauſe in that ſtate, no man is reputed a perfect comſummate <hi>Chriſtian</hi> without the ſame: a marke, becauſe by the order of that ſtate, no<note place="margin">Rituall. Roman. in Ceremo de Baptiſmo, fine.</note> man is to bee admitted to receiue the bodie of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he haue the ſame. Finally, a marke moſt properly, becauſe in that ſtate, it is an Article of Faith, that by the<note place="margin">Cone. Trident.</note> vertue of the outward criſmaticall vnction, there is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed and ingraued in the verie ſoules of the anointed, an indeleble ſpirituall character: A marke then it is, and by it they profeſſe obedience to the <hi>Papall</hi> State, and can wee require more for the cleering of this point? I might here note others, yea and ſhew how they giue markes on the foreheads, or crowne of the head, or both, in their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie adminiſtration of the Sacrament of Baptiſme it ſelfe; not in regard of their baptiſing in the vſuall forme, <hi>In the</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Impious marking in their admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</note> 
                     <hi>name of the Father, &amp;c.</hi> but for that, they (holding naturall water not to be ſufficient, nor fit matter of the <hi>Sacrament</hi>) doe make a magicall and ſuperſtitious commixtion of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and oyles together: firſt of the holy <hi>oyle</hi> alone (ſo they call it) ſecondly, of <hi>criſme</hi> alone; and thirdly of <hi>criſme</hi> and oyle together. Thus they abuſe the ſacred <hi>Sacrament of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17704:22"/>
Chriſt,</hi> and with ſuch charmed and commixt waters and oyles, they marke all their followers in their foreheads.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the <hi>Papalls</hi> taking of the Beaſts marke in their hands, I firſt paſſe by (becauſe it is not generally of them all) the ſuperſtitious vnction, which their <hi>Deacons</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> (at their taking of Orders) doe take into their<note place="margin">Matt. 24. 24.</note> handes; in regard whereof it may bee probably thought that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is pleaſed (if wee ſtand to the plaine litte<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>all ſenſe) to haue fore-prophecied againſt them, vnder the name of <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>falſe Chriſts, falſe anointed-ones:</hi> This marke (I ſay) I paſſe by. The firſt marke that I note, is that their taking in their hands (for it is common to them all) the marke of their ſuperſtitious woodden or ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer<note place="margin">
                        <hi>I call them blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous</hi> Agnus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyes, <hi>for that they hold the ſame,</hi> Depellere omne malignu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>to driue away all euil, yea,</hi> Pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> frangere, &amp;c. <hi>to breake and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy ſin, as the bloud of Chriſt, yea there is no good which they they do <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ot bring, no euill which they doe not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue; witneſſe thoſe knowne verſes.</hi> Balſamus &amp; munda cera cum Criſmatis vnda, &amp;c. <hi>Marks in the Papacy, and the ſame alſo Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian.</hi>
                     </note> Croſſes, their Graines, Beads, Medalls; but aboue all, their moſt blaſphemous <hi>Agnus-deyes</hi> (all markes, becauſe marked with ſome ſuperſtitious forme or other) whereby they acknowledge, a ſacred <hi>Soueraignty</hi> in the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> State: a <hi>Soueraigntie</hi> on earth, by the vſe of ſuch ſuperſtitious trumpery to remit all ſins, <hi>with a moſt full and plenary pardon;</hi> a <hi>Soueraigntie</hi> in the heauens, by the vertue of ſuch ſuperſtitious ceremonies to open heauen gates, therein to admit all the ſuperſtitious receiuers of ſuch marks: A <hi>Soueraignty</hi> within the bowels of the earth, thence to fetch out, from out of their imagined <hi>Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> poor patient ſoules, more or fewer, according as it ſhall ſeeme expedient, to the ſuperſtitious <hi>Bleſſer,</hi> or rather Charmer of the ſaid ſuperſtitious markes: And may not theſe bee iuſtly reputed <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> markes? markes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe really ſuch; markes, becauſe myſtically ſuch; diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing betwixt <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianity? Antichriſtian,</hi> for what more <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> then to tie remiſſion of ſins, the opening of heauens gates, the deliuering of poore patient ſoules out of Purgatory, to the ſuperſtitious vſe of ſuch contemptible creatures? hauing no other vertue of ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification in them, then what the charme of <hi>Papall</hi> breath may preſume to haue giuen them? O impietie of impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties!
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17704:23"/>
a man dying, if hee haue one of theſe Papall markes of graines, or meddals, &amp;c. in his handes, if hee can but ſay, <hi>Ieſus</hi> in his heart, hee ſhall aſſuredly haue a <hi>plenary</hi> pardon<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Papal blaſphemy.</hi> Idulgent. variae conceſſ. Colleg. Angl. &amp; Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratr nuper. pro laborantibus apud Indos.</note> and remiſſion of all his ſinnes: but if hee want, or haue no ſuch graine, then no ſuch aſſurance: ſo they rather blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme, then affirme.</p>
                  <p>Again, another <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> marke taken in the hand, in the <hi>Papall</hi> State, I note this: That then, when thoſe of that Synagogue, are made <hi>Catechumens</hi> (which to ſpeake ordinarily they muſt bee before they bee baptized) the Prieſt muſt put into their right handes the ſigne of the Croſſe; which ſigne or marke of the Croſſe, I doe not by<note place="margin">The Croſſe ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlitiouſly abuſed a marke of the Papall State.</note> any meanes call Antichriſtian, for ſo much as it is a ſigne commemoratiue or remembrance of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Croſſe; but I doe boldly and confidently call it <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> as it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed by them in that ſtate: for they moſt flagitiouſly pretend; that the putting of the ſaid marke, or ſigne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of thoſe that are to bee baptiſed, is a neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie preparation for the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> and the due receiuing of the ſame; and againe, for that by that very ſigne and marke ſo made, they promiſe defence againſt <hi>Satan,</hi> perſeuerance in faith, and after death life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ordo Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>endu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Catechumenum</hi> This marke, ſuch as receiued it not being baptiſed Infants, doe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards take it, yea ſome at the ſtate of men and women. A maine obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on anſwered.</note> for thus ſaith the Prieſt, <hi>Trade tibi ſignaculum Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini noſtri Ieſu Chriſti in manu tua dextra, vt te ſignes &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſam partem repellas, &amp; in fide Catholica permaneas, &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas vitam aeternam, &amp; viuas in ſecula ſeculorum. I deliuer thee in thy right hand, this ſigne of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that thou mayſt ſigne thy ſelfe, driue away the aduerſe part (the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill) that thou mayſt perſeuere in the Catholike faith, mayſt haue life euerlaſting, and liue for euer and euer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here (to anſwere an obiection by the way) we may not thinke, that the <hi>Papall</hi> State, may bee cleered from the iuſt imputation of <hi>Antichriſtianiſme,</hi> for that together with their vaine vnctions, and charmed oyles, in their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Sacraments,</hi> or <hi>Sacramentalls</hi> (as they ſpeake) they doe ioyne the name of the <hi>Father, Sonne,</hi> and <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> or for
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17704:23"/>
that they doe call on the mercies of <hi>God;</hi> or for that they doe withall vſe the ſigne of the <hi>Croſſe:</hi> no, no, this will not ſerue the turne; for it is moſt certaine (by expreſſe te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of Scripture) that the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> State, muſt be a <hi>myſtery,</hi> not an impudencie of Iniquitie: A State ſo ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling<note place="margin">2. Theſſ 2.</note> and powerfully working miracles, euen in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple<note place="margin">The Papall State Antichriſtian, though they call vpon the bleſſed Trinitie, and the mercies of God in their ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous rites.</note> of God; that the <hi>very Elect will be in danger to bee ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced:</hi> A circumſtance ſo plaine, and ſo important; that to mee, they ſeeme no leſſe then to dote, who affirme that Antichriſt ſhall deny the <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> for what dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſeducing to the <hi>Elect,</hi> where <hi>Chriſt</hi> is flatly denied? No, no, the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> State will pretend to be the very <hi>hornes of the Lamb;</hi> a very <hi>Vice-gerency</hi> inſtead of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſuch in truth is the Genuine ſignification of the word<note place="margin">
                        <hi>See</hi> Stephanus, <hi>and all the Greek</hi> Lexicons. <hi>See</hi> Matth. 17. 27. &amp; Matth. 20. Luke 11. 11.</note> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, for, according as the Prepoſition <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> may bee taken, it ſignifieth both one in the ſtead and lieu of Chriſt, and alſo one moſt oppoſite to Chriſt; and ſuch a one indeed ſhall Antichriſt be: He ſhall pretend to come in the name of Chriſt, and yet ſhall hee be moſt oppoſite to Chriſt, euen to the vtter perdition of the true follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Chriſt.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>The Magicians, Witches, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurers call vpon the name of God, vſe Croſſes, both materiall and tranſions, yea the Papall</hi> Arto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theos <hi>God in bread.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Though the <hi>Magicians</hi> (as it is moſt certaine) though <hi>Witches</hi> (as it is a thing knowne) though <hi>Coniurers</hi> (a thing likewiſe cleere) doe vſe to call vpon the name of <hi>God,</hi> and the holy <hi>Trinity</hi> in their abominable practiſes; though they vſe frequent and often <hi>croſſings,</hi> yea can doe (in ſome buſineſſe) nothing without <hi>croſſes;</hi> though they haue many <hi>materiall croſſes, ſacred oyles, hallowed waters,</hi> yea the <hi>Papalls</hi> owne <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>Hoſts;</hi> which they doe vſe and abuſe in their moſt execrable exerciſes: yet I hope, no Intelligent <hi>Papall</hi> will deny, but that ſuch their practiſes may be iuſtly called abominable, flagitious, and of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill: though in them (I ſay) they vſe often <hi>croſſes, croſſings,</hi> with <hi>recroſſings;</hi> yea, with adoring of their <hi>conſecrated Hoſts,</hi> and callings vpon the name of the <hi>Father, Sonne,</hi> and <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and of the <hi>holy Angels,</hi> and of the <hi>bleſſed Virgin</hi>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:17704:24"/>
her ſelfe: Why then, ſhall wee bee doubtfull to call theſe practiſes of <hi>Popery Antichriſtian,</hi> though they adioyne to their fopperies and impieties, the Inuocation of the name of <hi>God,</hi> and though they vſe therein the ſigne of Croſſe:<note place="margin">The ſigne of the Croſſe may be vſed as a lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ceremony, if voyd of ſcandall.</note> the which, though it may bee vſed as a laudable ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie (where iuſt ſcandall is not giuen) yet, as it is abuſed in the <hi>Papall</hi> State, I boldly call it (and ſuch like) <hi>Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> and markes of the <hi>Beaſt: Antichriſtian,</hi> becauſe deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (in the name of <hi>Chriſt</hi>) as efficacious for temiſſion of ſinne, for increaſe of grace, for defence againſt <hi>Satan;</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for the ſame end, no inſtitution nor command from <hi>Chriſt: Antichriſtian,</hi> becauſe perſwading vs to looke for remiſſion of ſinnes, otherwiſe then by the bloud of <hi>Chriſt: Antichriſtian,</hi> becauſe drawing our confidence from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and placing it in the ſeruile vſe of contemptible creatures: Concluding this point, I anſwer an obiection, which thus may bee made. The marke of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> is but one, but<note place="margin">The Anſwere.</note> then, can they bee the marke of the Beaſt, Except many may bee thought to ſtand for one? I anſwere, True it is, that the word of the Scripture, is here deliuered in the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular<note place="margin">How the markes of the Beaſt, both many, and one.</note> number; marke, not markes: yet, for that the ſaid Scripture affirmeth, that it is to bee <hi>taken in hand and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> (either ioyntly or ſeuerally) it inſinuates the markes to bee more then one; and this is agreeing to the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation<note place="margin">
                        <hi>See</hi> Lira alios.</note> of diuers of the Ancient, who by the marke in the forehead, vnderſtand open <hi>profeſſion by mouth;</hi> by the marke in the hand ſome publike act of obedience, or ſome profeſſion by oath, by laying downe, lifting vp, or putting forth hand or finger: But what neede wee to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the Authoritie of men, when as the Scripture it ſelfe tells vs (explicating it ſelfe) that no man ſhall bee allowed<note place="margin">Apoc. 13.</note> either to buy or ſell, who <hi>hath not either the marke of the</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The markes of the Beaſt more then one,</note> 
                     <hi>Beaſt, or the name of the Beaſt, or the number of his name:</hi> Loe here, not one, but three; except we ſhall not diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh that, which the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> hath ſo diſtinguiſhedly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17704:24"/>
deliuered vnto vs: or that the <hi>name</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> or the number of his name, ſhall not be expreſſed by ſome cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious miſticall marke, either of denomination or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; of denomination to be called <hi>Latines</hi> or <hi>Romans,</hi> after the number of the name; or by profeſſion to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the <hi>Italike Church,</hi> or to bee called <hi>Papiſts</hi> after the<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Papiſts</hi> the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and vnrefu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable name of our Aduerſaries.</note> name of the <hi>Beaſt, Papa,</hi> or ſome ſuch like. I ſay <hi>Papiſts</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the name of the <hi>Beaſt:</hi> for ſince the decree of <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeuenth, cleere it is that <hi>Papa</hi> is arrogated as a name pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to the <hi>Pope,</hi> and doth ſignificantly expreſſe the<note place="margin">Dictatus Greg. 7. apud Baron. ann. 1175.</note> whole ſtate of <hi>Papacy:</hi> after which, the profeſſours of that State (becauſe by faith they beleeue the <hi>Pope</hi> to be the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Head thereof) ought not to refuſe (if they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand themſelues) to bee called <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or <hi>Papalls,</hi> no they ought rather to glorie in the ſame name: Howſoeuer of this, cleere it is, that the <hi>Admirers</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> may haue more markes then one, and yet theſe more (whether two or three) may be called one; becauſe they agree in one analogicall reaſon and reſpect, of appertaining and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Beaſt, and this is (without queſtion) the ſenſe and intent of the Holy Ghoſt, that no man ſhall bee permitted either to buy or ſell, in the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> ſtate; who by ſome publike marke of profeſſion, or obedience, ſhall not ſubject himſelfe (in a verie Soule-ſubiection) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Now come we in few words to declare, how that no man who wanteth ſuch markes, as are aboue expreſſed,<note place="margin">No man permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d to buy or ſell in the papal ſtate, who wanteth the former markes, or ſome of them</note> may be permitted <hi>either to buy or ſell</hi> (ſo our <hi>Prophet</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) within the State of the <hi>Popes</hi> Dominions. A moſt fearefull calamitie, denoting an vniuerſall <hi>Apostacie</hi> and defection; deſigning alſo the ſtate of the true <hi>Church,</hi> for the whole time of <hi>Antichriſts</hi> reigne, to be obſcure, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible, &amp; vnconſpicuous, as being not allowed any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner<note place="margin">The true <hi>Church</hi> inconſpicuous in the time of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</hi>
                     </note> of commerce or ſocietie at all: what more apparent? And is not this very thing (to diſpatch all in a word) <hi>the very ſelfe-yoke of the Exactor,</hi> and of that oppreſſion, which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17704:25"/>
by the <hi>Pope,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> laid vpon all Perſons whatſoeuer, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe or contemne the markes aboue expreſſed? Let our <hi>Aduerſaries</hi> (a moſt fit name for the Papiſts) ſhewvs, if they can, any State, Kingdome, or Common-wealth (where the <hi>Papall Canons</hi> are not limited, or moderated by the Temporall Magiſtrate) in which any man or perſon, may be permitted either to buy or ſell (that is, to haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny peaceable commerce or ſocietie at all) who refuſeth or contemneth the aboue-expreſſed markes.</p>
                  <p>What elſe, but refuſall and contempt of the ſaid markes (ſince the abſolute reigne of <hi>Popes,</hi> in the <hi>Temple</hi> of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caied <hi>Chriſtianitie</hi>) hath cauſed ſo many commotions and ſubuerſions of States and Kingdomes? What elſe, hath beene the Lake and Head of ſo many fearefull hideous maſſacres? of ſuch immane diſquiſitions, and Inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?<note place="margin">Refuſall of Papal markes, cauſe of infinite calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties &amp; oppreſſions</note> of ſuch mercileſſe ſtranglings and burnings? of ſo many rebellions, &amp; inſurrections? what elſe hath brought forth ſuch an infinity of thunderclaps? of Interdicts and Excommunications? of threats and depoſitions? of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonments and proſcriptions, what tongue can number them all? what heart can ſufficiently deplore them all? Preſent examples hereof wee haue, ſo that he is a plaine ſtupid, who obſerueth them not; hee deſerues not the name of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> who condoles them not; neither is he worthy the name of a zelous <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> who to the vtmoſt of his power, withſtands them not. And thus haue I, by many reaſons, ſuppoſitions, and demonſtrations, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and deliuered, that, which his moſt Excellent <hi>Maieſty</hi> hath in a few lines moſt ſolidly and Chriſtianly objected, in his moſt Chriſtian <hi>Praemonition</hi> (a <hi>praemonition</hi> worthy eternall memory) to Chriſtian Princes; to weet, <hi>That the Papall State, is the very State of the Beast:</hi> My interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and expoſition then, of this Text, in this place, and at this time, may not come vnwelcome, which commeth countenanced, by ſuch an Authoritie; <hi>Great is Truth, and is will preuaile.</hi> And ſo a few words of our laſt Part, the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17704:25"/>
dreadfull threat, and denuntiation of <hi>Gods</hi> wrath, againſt the followers and <hi>Admirers</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>The ſame ſhall drinke of the wine of Gods wrath, which is<note place="margin">Third Part.</note> powred out without mixture into the cup of his indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. And he ſhall be termented with fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, in the preſence of the holy Angells, and in the preſence of the Lamb. And the ſmoake of their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſcendeth vp for euer and euer.</head>
               <p>HEnce-from we muſt learne a leſſon of inſtruction, to lay to our hearts, and to fixe in our remembrances, this fearefull denuntiation of the <hi>Angel,</hi> againſt all thoſe, who <hi>ſhall either worſhip the Beaſt, or the Image of the Beast; or who ſhall receiue the Beaſts marke, either in their hands, or on their foreheads; that they ſhall drinke, of the wine of Gods wrath, which is powred out without mixture, in the cup of his indignation; and that they ſhall be termented for euer, with fire and brimſtone, in preſence of the holy Angells, and of the Lamb.</hi> And who is not awaked? moued? yea, aſtoniſhed to heare ſuch a thunder? to obſerue ſuch a ſtorme? A thunder, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing from the breath of <hi>Angels,</hi> of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> and of <hi>Gods</hi> owne mouth: A ſtorme, not of fire alone, but of fire and brimſtone; not a nights-ſtorme, but an euer-during ſtorme, powred from out of the cup, of Gods heauieſt wrath and indignation: What more dreadfull; what more to bee dreaded? O religious cares, and <hi>Chriſtian</hi> hearts, let the feare of theſe things, teach vs to put on a ſpirit of reſolution and conſtancy, againſt the charmes and deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſorceries, of all the ſubdolous <hi>Hellens, Sinons,</hi> and <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyes</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Great warines to be vſea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons</hi> of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</note> of <hi>Aniichriſt:</hi> Thoſe, who are of ordinarie ranke, it may bee thought ſufficient for them (for the auoyding of eternall damnation) that <hi>they goe out of Babylon; that they adore neither the Beaſt, nor the Image of the Beaſt;</hi> neither doe <hi>take his marke in their hands, or vpon their foreheads:</hi> but for others, who ſway and beare Staues and Swords of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17704:26"/>
who ſit in the Chaire of <hi>Prelacy,</hi> if theſe (<hi>God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing put into their hearts to haue preached,</hi> and to haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten againſt the Whore: if theſe doe not endeauour (to the vtmoſt of their powers) <hi>to make her deſolate?</hi> What elſe ſhall remaine for them, but a fearefull expectation of <hi>Gods</hi> iuſt iudgement, together with the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> to drinke of the <hi>Cup of his indignation and of the dregs of the Violls of his fury?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay not this, as though any Chriſtian Magiſtrate may not ſuffer any peaceable profeſſours of the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> State to liue (yea to liue peaceably) within the precincts of his dominions: not ſo; for wee cannot but thinke, that<note place="margin">How worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the Beaſt may be tolerated</note> as their are <hi>ſtratagems</hi> in warre, ſo alſo that there are poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in. State: A wiſe Generall wil be content, to loſe ſome ſmall quarter of his Army, ſo the day may be his: A wiſe and Chriſtian <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> may in wiſdome giue way a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in one place, ſo that Chriſt may gaine more elſe where; eſpecially, if there may be any probable hope, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> may bee there preached, where (through the tyranny of Inquiſition) he is ſcarce yet truly heard of. <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the <hi>Emperour</hi> (being moued thereunto by the <hi>Arrian Biſhops</hi>) required of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> that the <hi>Arrians</hi> might be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed<note place="margin">Aremarkeable anſwere of <hi>Athanaſius.</hi>
                  </note> one <hi>Church</hi> at <hi>Alexandria:</hi> to which propoſition, that euer renowned <hi>Prelate,</hi> made this anſwere: <hi>Moſt willing</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>vpon this condition, that the Orthodoxe may haue one Church allowed them at Antioch:</hi> which his anſwer, though<note place="margin">Baron. Anal. An<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Do. 349. n. 15.</note> it ſeemed moſt reaſonable and equall to the <hi>Emperour;</hi> yet the <hi>Arrians,</hi> would none of it; ſo bad a cauſe did they maintain, and ſo loth were they to meaſure to others, with <hi>that meaſure: wherewith they would haue others meaſure vnto themſelues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And who is hee, if he be perſwaded that truth is with vs<note place="margin">Our Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries dare not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low one Church for two; not one Miniſter for three Popiſh Prieſts.</note> (as moſt certaine it is) and that alſo in the end, truth muſt and will preuaile? Who I ſay is hee, who would not wiſh with his whole heart that in all <hi>Cities</hi> and <hi>Townes,</hi> of any <hi>Proteſtant States</hi> and <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> that our <hi>Aduerſaries</hi> the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> might bee allowed two <hi>Churches</hi> and two <hi>Prieſts,</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:17704:26"/>
vpon this condition, that in like Cities and Towns (num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber for number) of any <hi>Popiſh Kingdomes,</hi> or <hi>States;</hi> the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and ſincere <hi>Chriſtians</hi> might bee allowed but one Church and one Miniſter. This option, though it may ſeeme vnequall (two againſt one) for as it is in the prouerb, Not <hi>Hercules</hi> againſt two; yet ſure I am (ſo great euer is the diffidence of Hereticks, and feare of thoſe that are falſe) that they will neuer giue their aſſent therunto: which being ſo, what a vanitie were it to thinke, that our Aduerſaries, ſhall euer bee able to preuaile by the way of truth? No, no, where they haue not the meanes of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, nor teeth of Leuiatham, and power of the Sword in their hands, there they are very feeble and weake; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it bee vpon ſome wanton and inſtable perſons (la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with ſinne) who thinke that to be a moſt facill religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which teacheth dames and maides, men and boyes, to disburden their loaded ſoules into a <hi>Prieſts</hi> lap; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and to bee abſolued, and then all to bee cock-ſure: for, ſay they, the <hi>Prieſts</hi> ſentence on earth, is alſo ratified in the very heauens; yea, though the ſentence bee giuen, wel-nigh in <hi>the very heat of the ſinne;</hi> yea more, <hi>in the gilt of cankeriated and ſeared conſciences, prepared and ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne (as the dog to the vomit) to the ſame ſinne againe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How vaine to thinke, that our Aduerſaries, ſhal be euer able to preuaile by the way of truth, when as their fingers neuer ceaſe (by additions, detractions, and immutations) to corrupt (they ſay to correct) Ancient <hi>Authors?</hi> when as they dare not ſuffer any of theirs to read any of our<note place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Azor. inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tut. moral. p. 1. l. 8. c. 16.</note> bookes? but curſe with bell, booke, and candle, all thoſe who (without ſpeciall licence) ſhall attempt the ſame? And though they may bee thought to deale diſcreetly, in<note place="margin">Manifeſt timidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the Popes, not to allow the reading of any of our bookes, no not to their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates.</note> that they doe not indifferently permit the reading of our bookes, to the promiſcuous multitude; yet that they ſhould not allow their learned Laicks; more, their learned <hi>Prieſts;</hi> more, their learned <hi>Paſtors;</hi> more, their <hi>Doctors</hi> and <hi>Prelates</hi> to read our bookes? What elſe can bee the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17704:27"/>
cauſe, but <hi>a conſcience of their own weakneſſe?</hi> On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, Truth goeth on ſo confident (like a Lion) and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious, in all <hi>Proteſtant</hi> States, or moſt of them; that wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigh an infinitie of <hi>Popiſh</hi> Authors are therein permitted; and yet, notwithſtanding ſuch an infinite libertie (which<note place="margin">How Popery to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated, and yet to little effect.</note> in a true ſenſe may bee called a toleration of <hi>Popery,</hi> euen in her cunningeſt and readieſt myſtery of deceit) yet how few, of our learned, iudicious, and vnderſtanding profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, are by ſuch meanes drawne away from vs to them? blaſts and puffs of diſcontent, do indeed driue away ſome from vs: But, ſhould ſuch a libertie of our bookes bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed amongſt them, it were not poſſible, but that the tenth (if not more) of theirs (both learned and iudicious) would repaire to vs: And is not this, an argument <hi>Oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſine,</hi> that truth is with vs, and not with them? And againe, that their bookes, though tolerated amongſt vs (to vſe <hi>Chryſoſtoms</hi> phraſe) do rather <hi>confirme and ſettle ſolid minds, then moue or ſhake them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chryſoſt in 1. ad Corinth.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thus much haue wee noted of their bookes tolerated: but (to adde a few words for your inſtruction) where (in any State <hi>Proteſtant</hi>) it may happen any <hi>Ignatians,</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Popiſh Prieſts</hi> and Friers to bee tolerated, or conniued at; what is the primeſt and onlyeſt weapon and meanes, by which they vſe to <hi>negotiate Soules,</hi> and to draw ſeduced fooles, into their net of perdition: ſurely, it is fraudulent <hi>latencie</hi> and ſeerecie; to worke in ſecret, not ſuffering them, whom they aſſault (if poſſibly they may bee ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded) to make knowne their attempts, to any of our learned <hi>Doctors</hi> and <hi>Paſtors. Carbo,</hi> conteſting and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing<note place="margin">The fraudulent endeuours of Popiſh Friers, &amp;c.</note> againſt <hi>Silla</hi> his ſworne enemy, was wonted to affirme of him: <hi>That in Silla hee fought both againſt Fox and Lion, yet that hee feared more from the Fox, then from the Lion:</hi> Our Conteſtation and oppoſition, being againſt theſe our moſt deuoted Enemies (<hi>Roman Sillas</hi>) we are in them to oppoſe both againſt Fox and Lion, yet (in my opinion) we may iuſtly feare, more from the Fox, then from the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17704:27"/>
Lion: I meane, more from their craftie ſubtilty; then from their open hoſtilitie and imm<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nitie. Amongſt all the ſubtilties of the Fox, his hole is the primeſt; Amongſt all the ſubtilties of the <hi>Ignatians,</hi> Friers and Monkes (where the publike face of religion is nor theirs, but they may onely happen to be tolerated or conniued at) no one<note place="margin">Their greateſt ſubtilty is <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency.</hi>
                  </note> ſubtiltie is like to that of their Latencie: who, as they (there) deſire to go diſguiſed in their habits, and to walke in many colours, and formes ſauing their owne: yea, and had rather be conniued at, to goe ſo diſguiſed, then to bee tolerated, to goe in their owne habits themſelues (<hi>for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſubdolo<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> workmen, they ſhun nothing more then the light:</hi>) ſo aboue all things they endeauour, that the perſwaſions which they vſe, to draw any from the truth, may be ſecret, latent, and not knowne: If then, the wiſdome of any <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> State, ſhould (for ſome high reſpects) thinke it<note place="margin">A neceſſary ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice.</note> meet to tolerate, or to conniue, at ſuch manner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; then, aboue any cautions to bee vſed, againſt their ſubtilties, diuices, and circumuentions; I dare be bold to giue this, and (in the feare of God, and in his preſence) to charge you with it; that ſo ſoone as any of you may bee aſſaulted, with their ſecret and ſugred perſwaſions (to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake <hi>Gods</hi> truth, and to imbrace their <hi>Idolo-many</hi>) that forthwith, and with all ſpeed, yee make the ſame knowne, to ſome learned and diſcreet Diuines: who, by the rule of reaſon, by the Authoritie of venerable Antiquitie; but, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all, by the ſacred Word of God (the rule of our Faith) may prearme you againſt all their ſuperſtitious, and ſophiſtical vanities: I ſaid before, diſcreet &amp; learned Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; for aboue all things thoſe who are ſo aſſaulted, muſt beware of thoſe men, who are <hi>Semi-Admirers</hi> after the Beaſt, I meane ſuch, who (who hauing put on the Dalma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Apoſtatizing ſpirit, or at leaſt, are beginning to put on the ſame) doe hold that the Papall Church, is the true Church of Chriſt; and that the obſtinate Papiſts, ſo liuing and dying (without repentance) are in the ſtate of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation:
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17704:28"/>
Further, who affirme and dare to dogmatize, that there are no Hereſies publikely defended and maintained in the Papall State; and that there is no fundamentall difference, betwixt the Roman and the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: and yet, leſt theſe Neutralizers ſhould bee taken in their hypocriſie, they will fairely mince the matter, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine their words: For, they will acknowledge the Roman Church to be (O Egregious) <hi>aliqualiter corruptam, in ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what corrupted:</hi> Theſe, theſe <hi>Sinoes</hi> yee muſt by all means auoid, for howſoeuer they ſeeme to bee ours, yet they are not in truth of vs; but are ready to goe out of vs, driuen by any blaſt of diſcontent, or allured by any gayle of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, and that wee haue now more ſuch amongſt vs, it ariſeth from the vanitie of falſe hopes and expectations. And yet let mee not here bee miſtaken, in that which I ſo reſolutely affirme againſt the ſaluation of Papiſts; or of their being in the ſtate of ſaluation: This I affirme, not of or againſt all, but againſt wilfull vnrelenting and vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentant Papiſts. For no doubt can be made, but that in the Popiſh Church, there are and haue bin diuers (which if wee will ſpeake properly, and according to the nature of termes, wee may not call Papiſts) who (ignorant of the <hi>altitudes of the Beast,</hi> or not obſtinately wedded thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to) are in the way of ſaluation: but I ſay of ſuch, that they are in the Popiſh Church, though not of the Popiſh Church, and that they ſuck onely, the good which is in that Church; but haue a reluctancie againſt the errours and ſuperſtitions; againſt the immanities and preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Beaſt, and of his State. If any one aske mee, how this can bee ſo: my anſwere is very facill; for that in that Church, there is the <hi>Creed of the Apoſtles;</hi> there are<note place="margin">How ſaluation may be thought to be had in the Popiſh Church.</note> alſo <hi>the holy Scriptures</hi> (though partly corrupted) why then ſhall it bee thought impoſſible, for many in that Church, to profeſſe the holy <hi>Creed</hi> in its true ſenſe? and to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace ſo much of the holy Scriptures (in the true ſenſe) as is neceſſary to ſaluation? And as for practiſe, moſt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17704:28"/>
certaine it is, that diuers in that Church, neither adore their Images; nor their God in bread; nor greatly heed praying to Saints; nor the <hi>Popes</hi> Supremacie; nor Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory flaſhes, with ſuch like: and as for <hi>Papall Pardons, Graines, Meddalls, Agnus-deyes</hi> (with ſuch like trumperies) they doe both ſcorne and deteſt them, though <hi>for feare of the Phariſies</hi> they dare not ſo profeſſe. Of theſe and ſuch like, I will confidently thinke and affirme, that they may ſo fairely bee in the way of ſaluation, as <hi>Nicodemus</hi> was,<note place="margin">Iohn 3. 2.</note> whilſt hee came <hi>to Chriſt by ſtealth in the night;</hi> and as ſome of <hi>thoſe thouſands</hi> were (of whom <hi>God</hi> to <hi>Elias) who had not bowed their knees to Baall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This point, I might further enlarge, and more fully confirme, but time permits mee not ſo to doe; yet time, (by your Chriſtian patience and leaue) ſhall yeeld mee li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, to giue a neceſſarie inſtruction vnto ſuch (if any ſuch heare mee this day) who <hi>trembling and fearing where there is no iuſt cauſe of feare,</hi> do fearefully preſage, and feare to themſelues, that there may happen (and alſo that the ſame is at hand) ſome generall fall, and change from Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion<note place="margin">A vaine feare of change of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, conuicted and reproued.</note> to <hi>Popery,</hi> in this renowned State and Kingdome. Againſt the vanitie of this conceit (though I nothing doubt, but that there are, who endeuour ſuch a fall, and moſt perfidiouſly endeuour it) let me thus confirme and arme you: That ſuch a thing is <hi>Morally, Royally,</hi> and <hi>Diuinely</hi> impoſſible: Firſt, it is morally impoſſible, that a Kingdome, ſo ſetled and eſtabliſhed in <hi>Chriſts Goſpel,</hi> ſhould euer indure to behold, the puppit playes of <hi>Popery;</hi> had the truth bin ſo eſtabliſhed in King <hi>Edwards</hi> reigne, as now (by Gods fauour) it is; wee ſhould not haue ſeene, nor heard of ſo ſudden a change, as was made preſently after: but what was the cauſe therof, the <hi>Calues</hi> of <hi>Bethel,</hi> were then freſh in remembrance; the Beaſt then but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into her conſumption with vs, the wordes of God there and then are fulfilled, when and where <hi>her fleſh is eaten, and her bones conſumed.</hi> The <hi>Goſpel</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:17704:29"/>
was indeed planted in King <hi>Edwards</hi> dayes, but not wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered before Queene <hi>Maries</hi> Tragedy. The good ſeed was caſt into the ground, but it rooted not, till it was watered (and after it was watered) with the blood of <hi>Saints;</hi> euer ſince, it hath flouriſhed as the <hi>Palme,</hi> and ſhall ſtill (God ſaying <hi>Amen</hi>) flouriſh, maugre the malice of Satan, and of Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>Caſt your eyes round about this preſent World, reflect your memories into Generations, al Generations paſt; and ſhew me (if you can) any State or Kingdom, which hauing once fully (fully I ſay) ſhaken off the <hi>Papall</hi> yoke, by a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect reformation, did euer ſetledly receiue the ſame again? How many pretended <hi>vnions</hi> of ſubiection (aboue halfe a ſcore) haue beene made, betwixt the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and of the <hi>Eaſt? and as yet they haue not ſetledly agreed, neither will they euer ſo do.</hi> The <hi>Muſcouian</hi> Empire, which is now of the <hi>Greekes</hi> beliefe, had it not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fall into the hands of the <hi>Turke,</hi> then into the Beares <hi>Feet?</hi> And is not ſuch the reſolued affection of moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed profeſſions &amp; States? Not for any loue they beare to the Turkiſh profeſſion (as <hi>Turce-Papizing Reinolds</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniouſly<note place="margin">Coluino, turc. lib. 7.</note> inferres and deduces) but for that, there is a Greater Clemencie in <hi>Turke,</hi> then in <hi>Pope;</hi> the later, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantly perſecuting with fire and faggot all reformed Profeſſors, whom the other Clemently tolerates, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiuely protects: as likewiſe he doth thoſe of the <hi>Papal</hi> faith, who are tolerated likewiſe (if peaceable) within the bounds of his <hi>Empire.</hi> And to conclude this point, where the light of the Goſpel hath beene throughly preached; and the puppet-like vanities of Popery haue been liuely diſplaied, it is not poſſible that any Intelligent or vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Nation, ſhould bee brought to creep to a <hi>wodden ſtocke,</hi> or to fall downe and adore, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a God of bread,</hi> which after digeſtion, is to be caſt in <hi>ſeceſſum, into the priuy,</hi> or which locked vp in a Tabernacle may be knawen by a Mouſe or Rat, or conſumed by Wormes, &amp;c. Thus is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17704:29"/>
and change of religion, in this renowned State (and what Stateſ-man knoweth not ſo much?) ſhewed to be morally impoſſible: more might bee added, I ſaid in the ſecond place, that ſuch a change was <hi>diuinely</hi> impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible; for how elſe (to diſpute probably, and why may not ſuch be the ſenſe of the Holy Ghoſt?) ſhall the words of God be accompliſhed, that thoſe States and Kingdomes,<note place="margin">Apoc. 17. 1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> which firſt <hi>loued the whore, ſhould afterwards hate her,</hi> yea ſo hate her, <hi>that they ſhould eat her fleſh, and conſume her bones with fire:</hi> and what is this elſe but to make her deſolate, without any hope of euer recouering her former ſtate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine? The Scripture ſpeaketh thus of all the haters of the whore; haters of the whore (I ſay) ſuch as make a perfect reformation, not in part, but wholly; not in ſubſtance on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but in ceremonies likewiſe; ſuch as eat and deuoure the delicacy of all her ſuperſtitious rags, and conſume the very body of her errours and hereſies; the Scripture affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming this of all the haters of the Whore, may we not with great probabilitie apply and aſſume the ſame to this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned State and Church, which is become as an Aſſyle and Sanctuary to all ſincere haters of the Whore, to all ſuch whom the Tyranny of the Whore and her Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates may force into exile; and to all ſuch whom the force of Truth may effectually moue to abandon all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection to the Whore. The Word of God is gone forth; and by what is alreadie happily begun, let vs bee moſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, that her vtter ruine will in time bee accompliſhed: what? if our diſguiſed <hi>Aduerſaries</hi> vaunt (to their decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Dames and deluded wantons) the contrary? what though our Luke-warme <hi>Laodiceanizers</hi> (halters betwixt <hi>Baal</hi> and <hi>God</hi>) dreame to the contrary; gaping after prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by ſuch meanes, which are neuer likely to come to paſſe? what? though the Couert-chaffe of <hi>Communion-Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants,</hi> doe now ſhew it ſelfe to be <hi>Church-Recuſants;</hi> drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming after we cannot tel what? what though there be ſuch ſhadowes of vaine hopes? The words of God muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, and ere it be long (hypocrites in all States &amp;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17704:30"/>
Churches, being to their ſhame diſcouered) <hi>The man of ſinne, and ſonne of perdition will bee brought to vtter ruine and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Change of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion royally im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible.</note> 
                  <hi>perdition: Come Lord Ieſus, come quickly.</hi> I ſaid in the third place, that ſuch a change was Royally impoſſible: For how poſſible, that our Religious <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſhould not bee <hi>Semper Idem, alwayes the ſame?</hi> How poſſible but hee, who hath gone in and out before vs in this holy warre? Yea more, <hi>Cecinit claſſicum, hath ſounded out his moſt Chriſtian &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Alarum;</hi> wherein the <hi>Papall State</hi> is moſt liuely and<note place="margin">Praemonit. reg.</note> learnedly declared to be the State of the <hi>Beaſt:</hi> and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there is more learning and Diuinitie, then can iuſtly be refuted by all Papall <hi>Rabbins;</hi> I adde, or by any of their diſſembling <hi>Fauourites:</hi> How poſſible (I ſay) that he, who hath ſo happily begunne in the ſpirit, ſhould end in the fleſh? Shall any of vs, dare to be ſo irreuerent againſt <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty</hi> (ſo <hi>Chriſtian</hi> a <hi>Maieſty</hi>) as once to thinke, that he will doe ought againſt the knowledge of his own conſcience? (a ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt) or that he will ſuffer, that truth to bee impriſoned, impugned, which his Royall Pen hath ſo learnedly and Chriſtianly defended and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? Far be all ſuch ſurmiſes from the hearts and tongues of all dutifull Subiects, who alſo euer will (as they ought) interpret, <hi>Arcana Regni, Secrets of State,</hi> in the beſt ſenſe. But if, we will not perſwade our ſelues, that ſuch a change is Royally impoſſible; in regard we haue a <hi>Religious, Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; Reſolued Prince,</hi> in all points of <hi>Chriſtianitie;</hi> yet let vs be perſwaded, that ſuch an alteration is Royally impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, in reſpect we haue an Intelligent, and a Politick wiſe <hi>Prince:</hi> for who cannot but know, that with ſuch a change he muſt put on, <hi>lugum exactoris, The very yoke of the Exac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour,</hi> and that he and his Succeſſors, muſt of Abſolute <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs,</hi> &amp; Soueraigne <hi>Commanders,</hi> become blind deuouts to <hi>Papall Breefs,</hi> and liege <hi>Seruants</hi> alſo to the <hi>Soueraigne Lord</hi> (of all Lords) the <hi>Pope.</hi> For in <hi>Papiſtry</hi> it is an <hi>Axiome, that the Nation and Kingdome, which ſhall not ſerue the Pope, ſhall, muſt, and ought to periſh.</hi> Let vs then reſt reſolued, that ſuch a change is altogether both vnlikely and impoſſible:
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:17704:30"/>
Let vs caſt off ſuch feares, &amp; rather take heed that our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries do not thinke that we haue conceiued any ſuch feare; for vpon ſuch conceptions, they will begin new <hi>ſtratagems,</hi> and will think the day to be halfe theirs, if they once apprehend that we are afraid of their preuailing.</p>
               <p>I ſum vp this my diſcourſe, and aduiſe thus; let euery ſoule here preſent, feare, leſt through demerits of our ſins, we may be drawne from the ſtedfaſtnes of our profeſſion; let vs alſo in deuor by force of truth, and firmneſſe of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, to draw the <hi>Papiſt</hi> from the <hi>Idolls</hi> of his <hi>Hereſies, Superſtitions,</hi> and <hi>Impieties. Vliſſes</hi> his followers ſtopt their<note place="margin">A neceſſary ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueat.</note> eares, ſo to eſcape the charmes of <hi>Circes; Vliſſes</hi> himſelfe (his eares being vnſtopped) binds himſelf faſt to the Maſt of the Ship, that ſo hee might eſcape her veneficious charmes: Yee that are but weake in zeale, or not fully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, ſtop your eare againſt <hi>Romes</hi> Charmers, charme they neuer ſo gloriouſly; but yee who are better inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and who dare to heare their diſputes, their conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, their arguments; tye your ſoules inuiolably to the Maſt of <hi>Chriſt</hi> his Ship, his ſacred Word; with the cords<note place="margin">
                     <hi>A true rule of</hi> Catholiciſme: Vincent Liti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenſis contra Hereſes.</note> of the rule of Faith; which rule is no other, then that forme of doctrine which is <hi>Catholike:</hi> that <hi>Quae ſemper, quae vbique, quae ab omnibus credita fuit; That doctrine which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, which in all places, and of all perſons hath beene beleeued.</hi> Vnder this Maſt only (<hi>Gods</hi> ſacred Word Catholikely, not Popiſhly interpreted) ſhall yee bee ſafe and ſecure, againſt all the nouell vanities, and vaine nouelties; againſt all the impious blaſphemies, and blaſphemous impieties; againſt all the arrogant preſumptions, and preſumptuous arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies of the Antichriſtian State of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let vs then, O <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ſoules! be reſolute &amp; conſtant for the teſtimony of <hi>Ieſus!</hi> he who lookes backe (hauing put his hand to the plough) is not fit for the Kingdome of God: neither is he fit for the religious chaſe, &amp; zealous purſuit, which is to be made after ſo execrable a <hi>Beaſt,</hi> who may either looke backe by returning, or withdrawing his
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:17704:31"/>
firſt works (like ſome <hi>Godleſſe Dalmatian Apoſtata</hi>) or who like ſome profane <hi>Helceſaean</hi> (diſſembling his Faith) may ſhake hands in ſomewicked communion with the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> or with theſe ſworne champions of the <hi>Beaſt;</hi> or finally, who like ſome <hi>Godleſſe Adiaphorizer,</hi> may either ſay in his heart or ſpeake with his mouth, that any man (ſo he profeſſe <hi>Chriſt,</hi> beleeue on <hi>Chriſt</hi>) may bee ſaued in ſuch his faith and profeſſion, be it <hi>Popiſh,</hi> be it <hi>Muſcouiſh;</hi> be it <hi>Pelagian,</hi> be it <hi>Donatian,</hi> be it of any other, <hi>falſly named, forme of Faith whatſoeuer.</hi> O <hi>Chriſt,</hi> what times doeſt thou ſuffer, when wee are thus enforced to ſpeake againſt ſuch an exceſſe of impietie and <hi>irreligioſity!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I conclude, the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> hath ſpoken, <hi>Mercy and Iudgement belongs to him:</hi> mercy from him, for all thoſe, who ſhall ſincerely ſerue and worſhip him; iudgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all thoſe, who ſhall worſhip the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> or the Image of the <hi>Beaſt:</hi> mercy for euer, for all thoſe who vnder the <hi>Lamb,</hi> are called choſen and faithfull; iudgement againſt all thoſe, <hi>Who ſhall receiue the mark of the Beaſt in their hands, or on their foreheads:</hi> mercy for all thoſe, <hi>Who may dye in the Lord, for they ſhall reſt from their labours:</hi> (which <hi>God</hi> of his infinit mercy grant to euery ſoule here preſent:) iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt all thoſe, who <hi>ſhall admire after the Beaſt; for they ſhall drinke of the cup of Gods wrath and indignation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From vs, who worſhip the <hi>Lamb,</hi> but abhorre the <hi>Beaſt;</hi> who onely adore <hi>Gods Word,</hi> but execrate the <hi>Beaſts Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions:</hi> From vs, who haue in hate all the markes and <hi>Characters</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and who are ſigned with the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of the holy <hi>Lamb</hi> in the day of our <hi>Redemption.</hi> From vs (I ſay) to our <hi>God,</hi> together with the <hi>Lamb</hi> that <hi>ſitteth vpon the Throne, and their euer bleſſed Spirit, be rendred bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, Claritie, power, wiſdome, honour, thanksgiuing, vertue, and obedience, from this time forth for euermore,</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17704:31"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
